<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="cpb4" n="4" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Commonplace Book vol. IV</title>
                <author>Mill, James (1773-1836)</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Encoded by Kris Grint.</p>
                <p>First published September 2010. This version published September 2015.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Based on a transcription of James Mill's Commonplace Books by Robert A. Fenn.
                    Volumes I-IV held at the London Library, volume V at the British Library of
                    Political and Economic Science (LSE).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p>This volume clearly contains some of the earliest material in the whole
                    collection. See <ref target="cpb4ch25scrap173v">173v</ref>, for example, which
                    is obviously a note from Mill’s student days at the University of Edinburgh;
                    possibly the same may be said about the deleted material on <ref
                        target="cpb4ch22scrap160r">160r</ref>. Nearly all the sections begin with
                    early, approximately pre-1808, examples of his hand. There are a number of
                    indications, however, that Mill returned to this volume even late in life. At
                        <ref target="cpb4ch9scrap45r">45r</ref>, one finds the shaky, enlarged hand
                    of his last ten years. Also, at <ref target="cpb4ch4scrap10r">10r</ref>, there
                    is an obvious sign of Mill adding to an item from a later edition. Here he gave
                    a further reference to a Gibbon letter from the 1814 edition of the
                    Miscellaneous Works, having earlier quoted it from that of 1796.</p>
                <p>One of the most attractive features of this notebook is that it contains a far
                    larger amount of commentary, or reflection, on the text which he was quoting, as
                    well as notes not based on any text but rather on incidents or events of the
                    period in which they were written; see <ref target="cpb4ch1scrap1r">1r</ref>,
                    for example, for the comment on the 1806 election in Westminster, or <ref
                        target="cpb4ch6scrap13r">13r</ref>, for an incident from 12/7/1820. The
                    material in <ref target="cpb4ch20">§ 20</ref> may well reflect Mill’s work as a
                    reporter for the <emph>St. James’s Chronicle</emph> in the early stage of his
                    career in publishing from 1803 to 1807; see also <ref target="cpb4ch5scrap12r"
                        >12r</ref> for another.</p>
                <p>Some sixteen pages have been torn out of this volume: one before 1r, and between
                    155v-156r, two between 37v-38r, 52v-53r, 59v-60r, 166v-167r, three between
                    87v-88r and 172v-173r. In at least one place (<ref target="cpb4ch22scrap161v"
                        >161v</ref>) a pasted in note comes from paper of this volume. Some of the
                    scraps in <emph>CPB</emph> V may also come from this source, as may a few of the
                    pieces in <emph>CPB</emph> II. But as Volume V is in the Mill-Taylor collection
                    and thus separated from the other volumes in the London Library, no comparison
                    could be made of bits of it with the paper in this volume. In order to compare
                    the scraps in II with the paper in <emph>CPB</emph> V, one would have had to
                    lift them from the surface to which Mill glued them; hence this has not been
                    done. At <emph>CPB</emph> III <ref target="cpb3ch4scrap96r">96r</ref> there is a
                    reference to a section in this notebook which seems no longer to be extant; it
                    may well have been on one of the torn-out pages. Why Mill removed pages cannot
                    be fully explained, though one may suggest that he wished to re-arrange his
                    accumulated note material after the completion of his <emph>History of British
                        India</emph>. <emph>CPB</emph> II certainly represents an effort at such
                    re-ordering.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch1" n="1" type="chapter">
                <head>Commentary on a Speech by Sheridan</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch1scrap1r" n="1r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Mr. Sheridan, on the hustings at Westminster in the year 1806, after his
                        daily repetition of the boast how carefully he had maintained the language
                        of a gentleman, with what strictness he had observed all the elegancies of
                        decorum, told the multitude they might stare at hearing that he had met with
                        Mr. Paull in the company of gentlemen. Mr. Paull should have asked: Is this
                        the temperate language, is this the sensitive elegance of the knight of the
                        buskin, which cannot descend to personalities? Is this the refinement which
                        he has learned in the company of <del>the great</del> gentlemen, of whom he,
                        no doubt, is a most worthy and proper companion? No one needs to stare at
                        seeing him in the company of gentlemen, considering from whom he is
                        descended, the honourable life he has led, and the virtuous lessons they may
                        receive from <del>his company</del> him. Much would it import the good of
                        this nation that all her gentlemen and all her leading men, should
                        sedulously court the company of Mr. Sheridan. Above all it were highly to be
                        wished, that all her young gentlemen and noblemen should engross his
                        presence. Then instead of debauchees, sots, loiterers, who <del>whom no duty
                            can engage</del> spend the night in carousing, and the day in sleep, we
                        should have them models of temperance, men of virtue and industry,
                        honourable in themselves, and useful to their country. Instead of exerting
                        their gentleman like qualities in devising stra[ta]gems, to elude the just
                        demands of their creditors, to their ruin often and destruction, we should
                        find them all able to pay their debts, and with something to <del>the
                            good</del> shew to the service of their country, not driven by their
                        necessities to become common sponges, <del>the blood suckers of the</del>
                        devourers of the bread of the people.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch1scrap1v" n="1v" type="scrap">
                    <p>Gentlemen, he says, he has seen me [Paull] in the company of gentlemen. Does
                        he mean that description of gentlemen with whom his life has been most
                        connected, the kings and queens, the lords and ladys of the playhouse? You
                        might indeed stare if he could tell you with truth that he had seen me
                            <del>there</del> among them.</p>
                    <p>Observe my friends, the hypocrisy of this man. Just now with fawning accent
                        he calls you gentlemen. But you see he does not mean so. For there is
                        another class of persons to whom alone he thinks the name really belongs,
                        and of whose company he tells you I am not worthy. But let us take him at
                        his present word. You then are gentlemen. <del>according to him</del> Tell
                        us then yourselves whether you would think me or Mr. Sheridan least worthy
                        of your company? Whom would you like best to come into your shops as a
                        customer?</p>
                    <p>He tells you I am unworthy to be seen in the company of gentlemen. <del>You
                            and I will</del> Whether do you think, gentlemen, that the man whose
                        means, whether great or small, are completely equal to his wants, whose
                        circumstances are totally independent, or the man whose wants are infinitely
                        beyond his means, the bread of whose mouth, and what to some people is of
                        more consequence the drink, depends upon the smile of a patron, and must be
                        gained by securing his favour, which of these two men is least likely to do
                        any thing unworthy of a gentleman?</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch1scrap2r" n="2r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Gentlemen, in regard to birth, I am what many kings might be proud to be, I
                        am the son of an honest, independent, commoner of Great Britain. Gentlemen,
                        this is the <del>envied</del> enviable lot of the greater proportion of you.
                        What shall I say; would not the greater proportion of you think it an insult
                        to have his birth compared with that of the Treasurer of the Navy? Whose son
                        is he? In the first place he has better luck than most of his
                            <del>profession</del> tribe if he can tell. But who was the man who was
                        married to his mother? Why a <del>vagrant</del> person whom the law of this
                        country looks upon in a light next to that of the gypseys, a strolling
                        player, a species of idle deceivers of the people, whom the law directs to
                        be coerced as rogues and vagabonds.</p>
                    <p>Compare the lives that this companion of gentlemen and I have led, and say
                        which of us is most worthy of the company of <del>gentlemen great men</del>
                        honourable men? My occupations have been those which have raised to
                        distinction some of the most honoured names in your history, the active
                        enterprises of trade, those occupations on which the superiority of your
                        country so essentially depends. What have been the occupations of my
                        opponent? Need I describe them gentlemen? Is there a worthless creature,
                        reduced by his debaucheries to cry ballads about the streets, who <del>needs
                            to be as ashamed of</del> would not gain by the comparison?</p>
                    <p>Which of his talents, gentlemen, is it that recommends him to the company of
                        gentlemen? Is it his honourable birth; the independence of his condition;
                        the unspotted purity of his life; Is it <del>gentlemen</del> his justice and
                        integrity? By what name gentlemen, do you call the man, who setting up an
                        appearance beyond what he can support draws in tradesmen</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch1scrap2v" n="2v" type="scrap">
                    <p>to <del>send</del> give him goods and credit, to an amount beyond which he
                        can never hope, or intend to pay? You have too often fatal experience of
                        such characters. <del>The whole Kingdom knows for what worthy purpose Mr.
                            Sheridan / I need not ask of you for what honourable</del> Gentlemen,
                        the whole kingdom says that Mr. Sheridan is admitted into fashionable
                        company, because when half drunk he plays the buffoon well. We read of an
                        old drunken buffoon, a greater wit than Mr. Sheridan, who formerly was a
                            <del>great</del> favourite with an heir apparent of this country. We
                        know too in what light this prince looked upon that old buffoon, when he
                        came to his senses, and had the duties of a king to perform to his
                        country.</p>
                    <p>What action of mine, gentlemen, have you ever heard of, which ought to
                        exclude me from the company of men of honour? What is the whole tenor of Mr.
                        Sheridan’s life? Is it like that of a gentleman? There is one quality,
                        gentlemen, in which Mr. Sheridan is known to stand the foremost in this
                        kingdom; and any less degree of that quality would not have supported any
                        man situated as he is, to have talked about the unworthy admission into the
                        company of gentlemen; that distinguishing virtue of Mr. Sheridan is
                        impudence. <note>Early hand. Sheridan’s remarks are in <emph>The
                                Times</emph>, 17/11/1806, p. 3b, in an account of one of Sheridan’s
                            speeches in the Westminster election: “I have met Mr. Paull before now
                            in <emph>gentleman’s</emph> company—Nay, Gentlemen, you may stare, and
                            it may perhaps surprize you; but I can assure you of the fact [loud
                            laughter].” Italics in the original. In the <emph>Morning
                                Chronicle</emph>, 17/11/1806, p. 2c, it is put differently: “I
                            myself have met him more than once at dinner in gentleman’s society—I
                            see your faces, gentlemen and seem astonished, but I assure you it is a
                            fact.” Earlier in the election Sheridan had remarked: “but there was one
                            thing he was confident they would not believe, that he had in this
                            contest shewn himself deprived of the mind and manners of a Gentleman,
                            though his adversary [Paull] had shewn himself woefully wanting in
                            both.” For further detail see also the <emph>Morning Chronicle</emph>,
                            15/11/1806, p. 3b. Sheridan barely defeated James Paull (1770-1808), the
                            radical candidate, in the election which terminated 21/11/1806. Paull
                            committed suicide in 1808 as the <emph>DNB</emph> discreetly puts it
                            “while in pecuniary difficulties.”</note></p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>I know thee not old man; fall to thy prayers.</l>
                        <l>How ill white hairs become a fool and a jester!</l>
                        <l>I have long dreamed of such a kind of man;</l>
                        <l>So surfeit-flamed, so old, and so profane;</l>
                        <l>But, being awake, I do despise my dream.</l>
                        <l>Make less thy body, hence, and more thy grace;</l>
                        <l>Leave wassailing; Know, the grave doth gape</l>
                        <l>For thee thrice wider than for other men.—</l>
                        <l>Reply not to me with a fool born jest;</l>
                        <l>Presume not that I am the thing I was;</l>
                        <l>For heaven doth know; so shall the world perceive,</l>
                        <l>That I have turned away my former self;</l>
                        <l>So will I those that kept me company.</l>
                        <l>When thou dost hear I am as I have been,</l>
                        <l>Approach me, and thou shalt be as thou wast;</l>
                        <l>The tutor and the feeder of my riots:—</l>
                        <l>Till then I banish thee on pain of death,</l>
                        <l>(As I have done the rest of my misleaders)</l>
                        <l>Not to come near our person by ten mile. <note>Shakespeare, <emph>The
                                    Second Part of King Henry the Fourth</emph>, p. 739, V, 5, ll.
                                48-66. The quotation was on a page tied to 2v, and written on a note
                                addressed to ‘R. Baldwin, Bridge St., Tuesday, Nov. 18<hi rend="sup"
                                    >th</hi>’ (the publisher Mill worked for 1802-07). The most
                                likely date is 1806 given the hand and the content of 1r-2r. Modern
                                editions have “God” for the common, eighteenth century variant,
                                “heaven,” at l. 61 and “gormandizing” for “wassailing,” at l. 57,
                                the latter not noted in the Variorum Shakespeare.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch2" n="2" type="chapter">
                <head>Hireling Scribblers</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch2scrap3r" n="3r" type="scrap">
                    <p>The hireling scribblers at present are busy persuading us that to protect
                        ourselves from Bonaparte, we must give up our liberties for a time into the
                        hands of the government. Once upon a time a horse was dreadfully oppressed
                        and threatened by a neighbouring stag. It came into his pasture, and
                        plundered at discretion; it offered nothing but blows as often as it was
                        challenged; and at last threatened to turn the horse out of his premises
                        altogether. In this emergency the man offered his assistance to the horse.
                        If you will let me get upon your back said he, and put a bridle in your
                        mouth, I will undertake to punish your enemy and his insolence. The horse
                        consented; but when his enemy was destroyed he found it impossible any more
                        to get the man from his back or the bridle from his mouth. Thus would it
                        prove with the unhappy people of this country. Let them once permit their
                        government to mount upon their back, and to fix a bridle in their mouths,
                        and let them never again expect to disengage themselves from either.
                            <note>Early hand, much like that of the Sheridan commentary (1806).
                            L’Estrange, <emph>Fables of Æsop</emph>, pp. 56-8, fable 57, “A Stag and
                            a Horse,” “Æsop’s Fables.” The political ‘moral’ is taken from
                            L’Estrange’s “Reflexion.”</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch3" n="3" type="chapter">
                <head>Three Speakers, A, B, and C. A Dialogue on the Theatre</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap3r" n="3r" type="scrap">
                    <p>A. You constantly sneer at the poor players.</p>
                    <p>B. It is a very childish prejudice, as most prejudices are.</p>
                    <p>C. Who the devil told you it was a prejudice?</p>
                    <p>B. Why, I think, it is very clearly a prejudice.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap3v" n="3v" type="scrap">
                    <p>C. Look ye, Mr. B., you tell us it is a prejudice, and your clear reason is
                        that you think it so. Now do you not perceive that in these circumstances
                        all you have pronounced, is a mere impertinence? What <del>possible</del>
                        right, Sir, do you claim to call any man’s opinion a childish prejudice,
                        because your notable self happens not to agree with it? If you have any good
                        reason to give us for admiring players, we will hear it; but even then, we
                        will not allow you to apply illmannered epithets to our opinions.</p>
                    <p>B. You are often as much pleased with the representations of players, as any
                        body.</p>
                    <p>C. Is that in your system of logic a good reason for admiring them?</p>
                    <p>B. Yes; I am always willing to give my approbation to people who give me
                        pleasure.</p>
                    <p>C. A most admirable rule for the distribution of approbation! Hear this,
                        gentlemen and ladies, Mr. B. distributes his approbation in proportion as
                        people give him pleasure. Are you prepared to defend this proposition, Sir,
                        or will you confess that you are reduced to an untenable proposition?</p>
                    <p>B. Shew me how it is untenable.</p>
                    <p>C. Will you not allow that there are certain sorts of people to whom bawds,
                        and the commodities which they keep yield pleasure? Ought we to bestow our
                        esteem upon these bawds and their commodities? To the receivers of stolen
                        goods no body yields more pleasure, than thieves and robbers. Ought these to
                        be the objects of our esteem? Do you perceive Sir, what a fine rule you have
                        fixed for the distribution of your esteem?</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap4r" n="4r" type="scrap">
                    <p>B. But these people ought not to receive pleasure from such doings. Their
                        pleasures are unlawful; and therefore there is no comparison.</p>
                    <p>C. But do you not perceive, my theatrical friend, that you are here taking a
                        different ground, you have shifted the scene upon us, before the act was
                        closed; you are now treading different boards; you have changed Characters;
                        you have run from Richard the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> to King Lear.</p>
                    <p>B. What do you mean?</p>
                    <p>C. It is not, you now tell us, the givers of any kind of pleasure that should
                        have our esteem, but the givers of certain kinds of pleasure. Have you any
                        definition then to give us of the kind of pleasure which is the proper cause
                        of esteem?</p>
                    <p>B. All lawful pleasure.</p>
                    <p>C. In the strict sense of the word, theatrical pleasures are not lawful; they
                        are prohibited by the law as much as bawdy houses are; and both are connived
                        at. But is there in your estimation Mr. B., any difference in lawful
                        pleasures?</p>
                    <p>B. What do you mean?</p>
                    <p>C. Is any of them more noble than another? As for example the nightman
                        procures us one sort of pleasure, and the philosopher another. Is there any
                        difference between those two? Or is the artificer of the one sort of
                        pleasure entitled to any more esteem than the artificer of the other?</p>
                    <p>B. Surely.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap4v" n="4v" type="scrap">
                    <p>C. There is then a gradation in pleasures; and according as the pleasure is
                        more noble, is the artificer more entitled to our esteem. Now, Sir, you who
                        understand pleasure so well, and make it even the standard and measure of
                        your esteem; will you tell us what is your rule, for fixing the gradation of
                        pleasures, in point of respectability?</p>
                    <p>B. Those which are applied to the mind I reckon more important than those
                        which are applied to the body; and of this noble kind are those of the
                        theatre.</p>
                    <p>C. Of this kind too are the pleasures of novel reading, of horseracing, of
                        gaming, of bruising matches. Well then all these, with the theatre, at their
                        head, are more noble than the art which raises food for man; the art of ship
                        building; the noble art of architecture. Will you, Sir, find many to join
                        you in this decision? Let us see whether one may not find a better rule. May
                        we not reckon that the most important pleasure, by the want of which man
                        would suffer the most? Now we believe there are few pleasures, from the want
                        of which man would suffer less than those of the theatre. Compare them. The
                        art of shoes, or breeches making are noble compared with these; so is the
                        business of the nightman.</p>
                    <p>B. But all these, being applied to the body, which is so much inferior to the
                        mind, are by nature less noble.</p>
                    <p>C. So then every art which procures pleasure to the mind is more noble than
                        any that procures pleasure to the body. What do you say to the art of
                        sycophancy by that rule? Does any thing procure more exquisite pleasure to
                        the vain mind?</p>
                    <p>B. That is not an art.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap5r" n="5r" type="scrap">
                    <p>C. Not an art? Ay, and one which has many professors. Who has not heard of
                        the art of the courtier? Wherein does the major part of it consist, if not
                        in sycophancy? Sycophancy not an art, say you? Has not Lucian written a
                        discourse, [<emph>The Dependant Scholar</emph>,] to deliver the precepts of
                        this art, which he lays down as distinctly, and regularly, as if he were
                        delivering the rules of rhetoric? Nay, are you so inobservant as not to know
                        that every <del>silly</del> vain man is likewise a professor of the art of
                        sycophancy? Is he not always eager to cajole and flatter every body who can
                        be prevailed upon to cajole and flatter him in his turn? Is he not always
                        ready to make the following treaty with any body? “Claw me, and I will claw
                        you.” But I do not wonder at your finding a difficulty in conceiving the
                        pleasure produced by the art of sycophancy, a man so little anxious about
                        praise, a man so exempt from vanity, a man of so much modesty, and
                        pretensions so measured and correct. But do not, Sir, draw an argument from
                        your own singular case against the pleasure which mortals less exalted than
                        you derive from sycophancy? What would become of kings and ministers, if it
                        were not for sycophants? But there is another thing, my dear Sir, to which
                        you have not adverted, with what skill and address many people play the
                        sycophant to themselves. Have you not often seen how effectually a man can
                            <del>often</del> persuade himself, that he is a man of exquisite genius,
                        a person of the greatest profundity and acuteness, of the most brilliant
                        imagination, and even a man of eloquence, when no other mortal can perceive
                        in him any thing beyond mediocrity, unless it be an overweening conceit. You
                        must allow then, my dear Sir, that sycophancy is an art of no mean
                        influence; and if you reckon the theatrical art, as I do, nearly on the same
                        bottom, we may soon be agreed. But I will go a little further than I am
                        obliged by any thing you have brought forward, which is all already
                        answered. I will point out to you the express causes which, in my opinion,
                        render the professors of your favourite art contemptible; and we shall then
                        see what you can produce to elude the conclusion.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap5v" n="5v" type="scrap">
                    <p>What do you think, Sir, of the art of buffoonery? In what class do you place
                        it? It is one of those addressed to the mind too. <emph>O imitatores, servum
                            pecus</emph>! [O imitators, a herd of slaves!] says the poet; and that
                        when the imitation only extends to the adoption of a man’s sentiments, or of
                        his stile and manner, with a view to make it one’s own. If this kind of
                        imitation reduces [men] to the state of cattle, and slavish cattle; what
                        degradation must be produced by the vile imitation, or mimicry of a man[’s]
                        features, of his gestures, of his voice, and that with a view only to create
                        amusement? “Pimps, buffoons, fiddlers, parasites.” <emph>Hudib.</emph>, P.
                        I, C. 2, l. 1016. <note>Butler, <emph>Hudibras</emph>, P. I, Canto II, l.
                            1016. Quotation inserted later. The Latin quotation is from Horace,
                                <emph>Epistles</emph>, B. I, n. 19, Loeb 383.</note></p>
                    <p>In the chusing of a line of life it is always a sign of an erect and manly
                        character to chuse those employments, however poor, which are least allied
                        to dependence; and those who seek out, and prefer those occupations which
                        necessarily imply dependence, which subject them, without redress to the
                        caprices of others, where it is necessary for them to court the favour of
                        others, and to dread the frown, which they must endeavour to escape by every
                        art of submission, and compliance, these persons may naturally be concluded
                        to be of base and grovelling natures; and with very few exceptions indeed,
                        every man in such a line of life, may be reckoned a slavish, degraded,
                        character. But in the whole train of the modes of procuring a subsistence is
                        there one which in so ignominious a way subjects the follower to the
                        caprices of others, as the stage? He displays himself to the meanest
                        rabble</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap6r" n="6r" type="scrap">
                    <p>for <del>a</del> hire, and gives them a right to <del>express to him</del>
                        treat him with the most offensive expressions of their contempt. The
                        ignominious usage to which he subjects himself is not private but public. He
                        lives by consulting the capricious humour of the basest of mankind. He is
                        the slave of the most irregular appetites and passions of his species. The
                        accidental humour of a woman lost to modesty, or a common bully may cover
                        him with hisses or applauses. Can any person who chuses an occupation of
                        this description be other than a person born to wallow in the dirt, a wretch
                        who deems himself worthy to be merely the sport of the passions of his
                        fellow creatures, a <del>wretch</del> grub who has not a desire to be a man,
                            <del>that is to act and think</del> who consents to be trode upon, who
                        acknowledges himself inferior to the meanest of mortals, and submits to
                        become their slave. He is beneath the lowest menial, sells himself to create
                        sport to that menial. It is impossible to speak of a woman who goes to
                        exhibit her person to a multitude, and by her exposures, her attitudes and
                        gestures, to satisfy their gross imaginations, <del>and give them
                            pleasure</del> without excluding every idea of modesty.</p>
                    <p>But let us analyse what the player does. There is a twofold division, which,
                        in a general way, expresses his whole business. He mimics either the weeping
                        man, or the laughing man. Now let us consider for one moment what we should
                        think of the man in private society, whom we should always, or commonly,
                        whenever he came into our company, put upon acting the weeping man, to give
                        us amusement; who could blubber, and sob and shed tears fictitiously,
                        whenever he was bid; who could twist his mouth, and other features into the
                        shape of weeping, as often as he</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap6v" n="6v" type="scrap">
                    <p>chose, and utter the doleful cries of a person in grief or pain. Should we
                        not think there was something illiberal and base in this mode of
                        entertaining our friends? What man of sense or feeling could bear the
                        thought of being this kind of companion among his acquaintances? But if
                        there is this indelible character of illiberality and baseness in such
                        exhibitions in private, the case is only exasperated when it is made public.
                        Add to this another character of baseness, and the ignominy is complete. If
                        the man whom we <del>should</del> despise for exposing himself in such
                        mimicries, when he does it gratis, and solely to give us pleasure, should
                        take money for his base exposures, what a wretch of meanness should we
                        account him? Yet this is what the player does; and for mimicries in public,
                        not in private.</p>
                    <p>If it be thus base to mimic the weeping man, it is plain the case must be
                        very similar to mimic the laughing man. The man, who in all companies into
                        which he goes, is considered as only capable to add to the amusement of the
                        party where he is employed to throw his features into the attitude of
                        laughing, to shake his sides, and utter the inarticulate, and convulsive
                        notes which accompany laughter, would undoubtedly be reckoned a sorry
                        fellow, as contributing to the pleasure of his companions by a very vile and
                        unworthy art, as a subordinate creature, who could not find out a better way
                        of contributing his quota to the general amusement. If any man does not feel
                        within himself how base would be the employment of having a man’s features
                        ever ready to throw, at command into those distortions; to distend his
                        mouth, to pull up his cheeks about his eyes, to half shut his eyelids, while
                        his eyebrows are at the same time thrown up, and his teeth exposed</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap7r" n="7r" type="scrap">
                    <p>like a snarling dog, and to force out a sound from his lungs by short
                            <del>interrupted, rapid</del> hitches, in the measure of a hiccup, or a
                            <del>convulsive</del> coughing fit, the sides working in unison, with a
                        painful and convulsive motion; if any man does not think that an employment
                        of his faculties in this manner to entertain his companions would not be
                        base and ignominious, if he needs any argument to convince him, if his
                        feelings are not sufficient, it seems impossible to find any instance of
                        baseness <del>with which</del> by comparison with which its ignominony can
                        be made apparent. For it is possible that after this he will reckon nothing
                        on earth ignominious.</p>
                    <p>A good reason may be rendered for that aversion which all direct, manly, and
                        sincere minds bear to this kind of prostitution. It is counterfeiting, it is
                        dissembling, it is <del>presenting</del> assuming a false appearance, it is
                        a violation of the reality of one’s character, it is an expression of that
                        which is not; a thing which even in shadow, and in jest, the honesthearted,
                        the plain, and the true cannot <del>bear relish</del> [get] away with. The
                        man who is given to it, who is much employed in it, they cannot think free
                        from contamination. It is a species of <del>abuse</del> violence to
                        sincerity, a <del>kind of</del> breach of the true, the real. And he who is
                        fond of it cannot easily be reckoned a very profound lover of the <del>true,
                            real</del> simple, and sincere. It is counterfeiting the passions which
                        a man does not feel; it is professing the sentiments which a man does not
                        entertain; it is pretending to be in circumstances in which <del>he</del> a
                        man is not placed. It <del>may</del> will be said all this is in joke. It
                        may be so; but <emph>hi joci in seria [?] ducunt mala.</emph> [These jokes
                        lead to serious ills.] <note>The phrase misremembered is “Hae nugae seria
                            ducent in mala”; see Horace, <emph>Ars poetica</emph>, l. 451, Loeb
                            487.</note> Habits of untruth are soon learned. A man whose profession
                        it is to assume false appearances; who must study confirmed habits of this
                        assumption, cannot easily be a man</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap7v" n="7v" type="scrap">
                    <p>of a direct, true, undisguised, simple, and sincere mind. He is given to
                        counterfeit. His mind is professionally disciplined to throw itself into
                            <del>a state contrary to its natural to the real an expression</del> an
                        appearance contrary to its actual state. It is far more employed in uttering
                        what it does not feel, than what it does. It is its business to study to do
                        this well. It places its glory in dexterous counterfeiting. It may be said
                        that this counterfeiting deceives not. Neither does that of the man who is
                        accustomed to tell wonderful and incredible stories about himself. But is
                        his mind nothing the worse for that? Does this habit of violating the truth
                        not corrupt all the principles of honour in a man’s breast? Does it not
                        lessen his respect for the truth? Does it not prepare him by degrees for
                        breaches of it, when something more than the vanity of an idle story is the
                        motive? It may be said the players do not intend to deceive? But do they not
                        intend to copy to the utmost perfection every sign of the false character
                        they mean to assume? Do they not mean to give you every appearance of an
                        angry man when they are not angry, of an affectionate man when they have no
                        affection, of a weeping man when they have no sorrow? Is not the habit of
                        counterfeiting all kind of feelings a bad habit? Does it not create a
                        factitious sort of character? If a man is much more employed in copying
                        imaginary feelings, than giving vent to such as are real; what sort of being
                        is he likely to become? A man in whom the habit of counterfeiting becomes
                        predominant. All nations have thought nearly in one way concerning players.
                        The Romans enacted a law that they should</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch3scrap8r" n="8r" type="scrap">
                    <p>not sit in an honourable place, at the public spectacles; “He who has
                        exercised the profession of an actor, is under no circumstances to be
                        allowed a seat in the first fourteen rows of the theatre.” [L] Quinct., Lib.
                        3, c. 6. We know how often, and in what contemptuous terms Demosthenes
                        reproaches Æschines with having been a player. <note>Quintilian,
                                <emph>Institutio oratoria</emph>, B. III, c. 6, § 18, Loeb 417;
                            Demosthenes, <emph>De corona</emph>, 180, Loeb 141. Early hand, much
                            like that of the Sheridan commentary (1806).</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch4" n="4" type="chapter">
                <head>Anecdotes: On Motivation in Human Affairs</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap8v" n="8v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“It is said that after the battle of Mariendahl [2/5/1645] M. de Turenne
                        spent the night in a mill. He slept with the miller’s wife. His aide de camp
                        appeared a bit astonished. My friend, the marshall said to him, one needs to
                        console oneself.” [F] Note et variantes au chant 21me de <emph>la Pucelle
                            d’Orleans</emph> de M. Voltaire. <note>In <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XI 396fn.
                            The battle, known also as Mergentheim, was a major defeat for Turenne.
                            In a very early hand (1802?). Next four paragraphs like the Sheridan
                            item above, p. 563, (1806).</note></p>
                    <p>When the ambassadors of Louis XI complained to him that the ambassadors of
                        the duke of Burgundy always lied, “You blockheads,” he cried, “that you did
                        not lie more than they did!” [F] Voltaire, <emph>Annales de l’empire</emph>,
                        p. 565. <note><emph>Annales de l’empire depuis Charlemagne</emph>, c. on
                            “Ferdinand III,” <emph>ibid.</emph>, XXV 511.</note></p>
                    <p>After the famous deliverance of Vienna from the terrible siege of the Turks,
                        when John Sobieski, King of Poland, the celebrated deliverer, went to church
                        to pay his devotions, on the memorable occasion, the preacher chose for his
                        text, “There was a man sent from God, whose name was John.”
                                <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, 524.</note></p>
                    <p>Prince Eugene characterised a war by an expression which might characterise
                        many more, <emph>il n’y a pas de assez de sujet pour faire tuer une
                            poulet.</emph> [There is not enough ground for it to justify killing a
                        chicken.] Coxe, <emph>House of Austria</emph>, v. ii, p. 100. <note>William
                            Coxe, <emph>History of the House of Austria</emph>, 1807, II
                            100fn.</note></p>
                    <p>Royalists are seldom so candid as the Emperor Joseph the Second. He was
                        asked, during the struggle for the independence of America, of the united
                        states, what party he was of. <del>I am a royalist by profession</del>
                        <emph>Je suis royaliste</emph>, said he, <emph>par métier.</emph> If he
                        meant by birth and prejudice he was right. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, 548fn.
                            In Coxe the phrase is in English and the French is not in the
                            text.</note></p>
                    <p>July 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1809. In his own house at Queen Square Place
                        Westminster, at dinner, Mr. Bentham told me, that his friend, George Wilson,
                        the king’s council, told him he had made many efforts to get Lord
                        Ellenborough to read Smith’s <emph>Wealth of Nations</emph>—but had not
                        succeeded. <note>This item in a <emph>slightly</emph> later hand than that
                            of the previous four paragraphs.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap9r" n="9r" type="scrap">
                    <p>“Sultan Firoze Shaw, ordered his favourite physician to be put to death, for
                        shewing more knowledge of astrology than his master—he was afterwards
                        induced to pardon him, but observed that “a complete physician should know
                        better from the human mind, that kings are like children and must be
                        flattered.” Ferishta’s <emph>Hist. of Deccan</emph> by Scott, v. I, p.
                        73.—Mr. Scott, observing how much this is in accord with the manners of the
                        orientals, says of them that “their children are seriously taught the
                        following maxim of the poet Saadee. Should the prince at noon say, It is
                        night, declare that you behold the moon and stars.” <emph>Ibid.</emph>
                        <note>Muhammad Kasim Ibn Hindu Shah, <emph>Ferishta’s History of
                                Dekkan</emph>, tr. J. Scott, I 72-3 &amp; 73fn.</note></p>
                    <p>It is a remarkable fact, and of which few have any idea, that it was a decree
                        of the National Assembly that put an end to slavery, to the state of <hi
                            rend="underline">serfs</hi> in France, and that at the time of the vote,
                        there were 1,500,000 serfs in the kingdom. Procés Verb., 7 Aoûst 1789.
                            <emph>Memoires de Bailly</emph>, v. iii, p. 20. <note>J.S. Bailly,
                                <emph>Mémoires d’un témoin de la révolution</emph>, Paris
                            1804.</note></p>
                    <p>Count Woronzov, the Russian Ambassador in England, frequently complained to
                        General Miranda of the vagueness and uncertainty of Mr. Pitt’s
                        communications. He said that, after a three hours conversation, expressly
                        carried on for the purpose of ascertaining the most important points, he had
                        found himself absolutely at a loss what to write to his court—what to say
                        had been the result of the conversation.—This anecdote was related to me, in
                        my own house at Pentonville, by General Miranda, on May 16<hi rend="sup"
                            >th</hi> 1810. <note>The reference is to Count Simon Woronzow,
                            1744-1832, resident, and then ambassador to Great Britain from 1789 to
                            1832. The story comes from Gen. Francisco de Miranda,
                        1750-1816.</note></p>
                    <p>De Ruyter, as well as Capt. Cook, was a common sailor—Franklin, a
                        printer—Socrates, the son of a fuller—Milton—Shakespeare—Locke—Newton—Gen.
                        [H.H.E.] Lloyd—all the great benefactors of mankind, poor—Luther, the son of
                        a blacksmith—Columbus—Faustus. <note>Several of the figures mentioned,
                            Milton, Locke and Newton, had anything but poor early lives. ‘Faustus’
                            is probably a reference to Johann Fust, one of the first developers of
                            the art of printing.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap9v" n="9v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“When Ld. Molesworth’s account of Denmark was first published, the Danish
                        ambassador complained to the King (William) of the freedoms the author had
                        taken with his master’s government, and hinted, that if one of his Danish
                        Majesty’s subjects had taken the like liberties with the King of England, he
                        would, upon complaint, have taken off the author’s head. That I cannot do,
                        replied the King, but if you please I will tell him what you say, and he
                        shall put it in the next edition of his book.” Hollis’s
                        <emph>Memoirs</emph>, v. I, p. 235. <note>Thomas Hollis, <emph>Memoirs of
                                Thomas Hollis</emph>, 1780.</note></p>
                    <p>Mr. Butler, the conveyancer, told me at Mr. Bentham’s, 11<hi rend="sup"
                            >th</hi> March 1811, that he passed a day with Fox, at St. Anne’s hill,
                        during the time of Addington’s Administration [1801-04]—that Fox appeared to
                        him merely an Eton boy, grown old—fond of classical literature—told him he
                        had never read Adam Smith; there was something in his doctrine about prices,
                        and exchanges, he never could get through with. <note>Smith, <emph>The
                                Wealth of Nations</emph>, B. I. Charles Butler, 1750-1832, one of
                            the most eminent conveyancers of his day, in 1791 became the first Roman
                            Catholic barrister since the reign of James II. He was a noted Catholic
                            apologist, and also assisted Bentham in several of his proposals for law
                            reform.</note></p>
                    <p>Bolingbroke was nearly made minister by George 1st who began to be tired of
                        the Walpoles. He gained the Dutchess of Kendal by £11,000, and Coxe
                            (<emph>Memoirs of Lord Walpole</emph>, p. 70) [said] “that the minister
                        was threatened with dismission, if he did not promote the return of
                        Bolingbroke, and that he compromised the business by consenting to the
                        restitution of his family estate; but counteracted and prevented his
                        complete restoration.” See too <emph>Memoirs of Sir R. Walpole</emph>, ch.
                        25. <note>Coxe, <emph>Memoirs of Horatio, Lord Walpole</emph>, pp. 70-1, c.
                            6; Coxe, <emph>Memoirs of the Life and Administration of Sir Robert
                                Walpole</emph>, I 196-203, c. 25. The Duchess of Kendal, 1667-1743,
                            was a mistress of George I.</note></p>
                    <p>The temporary loss of the imperial power by the House of Austria in the time
                        of Maria Theresa, would not have happened, but for the Emperor Charles the
                        Sixth, who would not obtain the nomination of his son in law, “under the
                        hope of having male heirs by a future marriage.” Coxe, <emph>Memoirs of Ld.
                            Walpole</emph>, p. 400. [C. 36.]</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap10r" n="10r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Lord Lokar(qur) from England in France, at the death of Cromwel. It was
                        asked, in jest, of whom was he the ambassador, Lambert, or Monk? He replied,
                            <emph>je suis serviteur tres humble des evenemens.</emph> [I am the very
                        humble servant of events.] <emph>Mem. de Monglat</emph>, t. 4, p.224. Quoted
                        by Anquetil, <emph>Intrigue du Cabinet</emph>, t. 4, p. 212.
                            <note>Louis-Pierre Anquetil, <emph>L’intrigue du cabinet, sous Henri IV
                                et Louis XIII</emph>, Paris 1780.</note></p>
                    <p>When the first Lord Holland, a fat, lethargic man, was in Paris, it was the
                        fashion to think every Englishman a deep philosopher; and Lord Holland being
                        a great Englishman must be a great philosopher. Once in a great company he
                        fell asleep, when a marquis pulling his neighbour by the sleeve, cried,
                            <emph>A voila, qui pense</emph>! [Ah there, he thinks!] Told by Lord
                        Charlemont, Hardy’s <emph>Life of Lord Charlemont</emph>, p. 122.
                            <note>Hardy, <emph>Memoirs of the Political and Private Life of James
                                Caulfield, Earl of Charlemont.</emph></note></p>
                    <p>The plan of the quack in Paris—His son a little boy walked before him, crying
                            <emph>Mon pere guerit toutes sortes des maladies.</emph> [My father
                        cures all sorts of distempers.]. The doctor, who walked behind, rejoined in
                        a grave and solemn tone, <emph>L’enfant dit vrai.</emph> [The child says
                        true.] Addison, <emph>Whig Examiner</emph>, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2.
                                <note><emph>The Whig-Examiner</emph> (21/9/1710), in
                                <emph>Works</emph>, 1856, ed. R. Hurd, IV 376. Translations from the
                            Addison text.</note></p>
                    <p>The history of John [<emph>sic</emph>] O’Neil, parish priest in Ireland—most
                        cruel treatment, in <emph>Cobbett’s Register</emph>, etc., 1804.
                                <note><emph>Cobbett’s Political Register</emph>, V 266-76
                            (25/2/1804), account of Peter O’Neil.</note></p>
                    <p>A fine letter of Sir William Jones [30/6/1781], indicating his noble public
                        spirit, to Gibbon—<emph>Miscellanies of Gibbon</emph>, v. I, p. 553, Lett.
                        151. <note>Gibbon, <emph>The Miscellaneous Works</emph>, 1796; 2<hi
                                rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. 1814, II 253-4, letter 151: “If my politics
                            have given offence; it would be manly in ministers to tell me so. I
                            shall never be <emph>permanently</emph> hostile to them, nor enlist
                            under party banners of any colour; but I will never resign my opinions
                            for <emph>interest</emph>, though I would cheerfully abandon them on
                                <emph>conviction.</emph> My reason, such as it is, can only be
                            controlled by better reason, to which I am ever open.” Mill’s reference
                            is puzzling; he has the right volume and page number for the 1<hi
                                rend="sup">st</hi> edition in 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> of 1796, the
                            right letter number for the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition in 8<hi
                                rend="sup">vo</hi> of 1814. But the letter number was added later,
                            possibly after he had the second edition, which he uses elsewhere, for
                            the most part.</note></p>
                    <p>When Lord Grey, deputy of Ireland, took prisoners that body of
                            <del>prisoners</del> Spaniards and Italians who invaded Ireland in the
                        time of Queen Elizabeth, “finding himself encumbered with so many prisoners,
                        he put all the Spaniards and Italians to the sword without mercy, and hanged
                        about 1500 of the Irish.” Hume, v. 5, p. 233. <note><emph>The History of
                                England</emph>, V 233-4, c. 41.</note></p>
                    <p>At the battle of Nieuport [1600] the prince of Orange put to death the man
                        who in the morning brought him the news of the defeat of his advanced
                        guard—lest it should terrify the troops. Mentioned by the Duke of Guise,
                            <emph>Mem.</emph>, p. 501. <note>Henri II, Duc de Guise, <emph>Les
                                Mémoires D’Henri De Lorraine, Duc de Guise</emph>, Paris 1681, B.
                            V.</note></p>
                    <p>The women of Russia bought Frenchmen from the Cossacs in order to have the
                        pleasure of murdering them and tearing them with their teeth.
                            <note>Obviously post-1812, but source undiscovered.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap10v" n="10v" type="scrap">
                    <p>Upon the execution of a traitor in Naples, during the time of his
                        administration, the Duc de Guise informs us, “The rage of the populace, of
                        the women, and of the children, was so great that they went [to the place of
                        execution] to tear him apart with relish, and the children went to him to
                        suck his blood. He was thus truly torn to pieces, even before he was dead,
                        and having his head cut off, nothing remained except the torso, all the
                        flesh had been torn off it, and pieces of it had been dragged through the
                        streets.” [F] <emph>Mem. de M. de Guise</emph>, p. 478. <note>Guise,
                                <emph>Les Mémoires</emph>, B. IV.</note></p>
                    <p>The Lord Keeper Guilford “had such a relish of the old year books, that he
                        carried one in his coach to divert his time in travel, and said he chose it
                        before any comedy.” North’s <emph>Life of Guilford</emph>, i, 27, 8<hi
                            rend="sup">vo</hi> Ed. <note>North, <emph>The Life of Francis
                                North</emph>, I 26-7. See Mill’s notes on North in Appendix I on
                            this and the following four remarks. From the second item on 10v to the
                            last item on 11v the hand is a later one.</note></p>
                    <p>Some curious particulars in the Life and Character of Judge Hales,
                            <emph>Ib.</emph>, 112-129. <note>[Mill’s reference is to Hale’s
                            partiality and bias in cases. See p. 113: “If one party was a courtier,
                            and well dressed, and the other a sort of puritan, with a black cap and
                            plain cloathes, he insensibly thought the justice of the cause with the
                            latter.” Hale was also vain and “an empty pretender.” See pp. 116-7: “He
                            published a short account of that noble Roman’s Pomponicus Atticus life,
                            and, at the entrance, a translation of the same in Cornelius Nepos; but
                            so ill done as would have brought the rod over the back of a
                            school-boy.” North concludes on p. 118: “In short, to give every one his
                            due, there was in him the most of learning and wisdom, joined with
                            ignorance and folly, that ever was known to coincide in the character of
                            any one man in the world.”</note></p>
                    <p>Anecdotes of Judge [George] Jeffries [Jeffreys], <emph>Ib.</emph>, ii, 95,
                        171-181. Ditto, of Sir John Trevor, p. 113. Ditto, Pemberton, 122.
                                <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, II 95, 171-81; 113-4; 122-3. All the
                            anecdotes reflect poorly on the honesty and sense of justice of these
                            men.</note></p>
                    <p>Curious history of Lord Chief Justice Saunders—at first a beggar boy.
                            <emph>Ib.</emph>, 125. <note>“He was at first no better than a poor
                            beggar boy, if not a parish foundling, without known parents, or
                            relations.”</note></p>
                    <p>Curious anecdotes of the leading men at court in Guilford’s time.
                            <emph>Ib.</emph>, ii, 134 <emph>et seq.</emph>
                        <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, 134-54. The remarks concern the manners of men in
                            the cabinet.</note></p>
                    <p><emph>Histoire de France depuis 1789</emph>, par Emanuel de Toulongeon,
                        praised as excellent by the editors of Mad. de Stael’s book on the French
                        Revolution, v. ii, p. 106. <note><emph>La révolution françoise</emph>, P.
                            III, c. XIV. The work referred to is Emmanuel de Toulongeon’s
                                <emph>Histoire de France depuis 1789</emph>, 4 volumes, Paris
                            1801-10.</note></p>
                    <p>The following observations on one of the particulars of Bonaparte’s character
                        apply exactly to Pitt, Fox, Sheridan, etc., etc. “Some have believed that
                        Bonaparte was well informed on every subject, because in this respect, as in
                        many others he made use of the tricks of charlatanism. But, as he had read
                        little in the course of his life, his knowledge was confined to what he had
                        picked up in conversation. By accident he may speak to you on any subject
                        whatsoever with exactness, and even with considerable science, if he has met
                        some person who gave him information on it immediately before; but the next
                        instant you discover that he does not know what every well educated person
                        has learned in his youth. Doubtless much of a</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap11r" n="11r" type="scrap">
                    <p>certain kind of talent—the talent of adroitness—is necessary to enable him
                        thus to disguise his ignorance, but none, except men enlightened by science
                        and regularly prosecuted studies can entertain just ideas of the government
                        of nature. The old doctrine of perfidy succeeded with Bonaparte, only
                        because he added to it the delusions of victory. Without this fatal
                        association there would not have been two opinions concerning such a man.”
                        [F] Mad. de Stael, <emph>Rev. Franç.</emph>, ii, 249. <note><emph>La
                                révolution françoise</emph>, II 248-9; <emph>The French
                                Revolution</emph>, II 246-7, P. IV, c. 3.</note></p>
                    <p>Johnson arraigned George II as, upon all occasions, cruel, unrelenting, and
                        barbarous. Instances. <emph>Life</emph> by Boswell, i, 124, 5, Ed. 2.
                            <note>Boswell, <emph>The Life of Johnson</emph>, (1739), I 124-5. The
                            examples given are those of an officer struck off the army list, and the
                            execution of a blameless participant in the 1745 uprising.</note></p>
                    <p>When the Emperor, Charles V, read upon the tomb of a Spanish nobleman, “‘Here
                        lies one who never knew fear,’ [he] said, ‘Then he never snuffed a candle
                        with his fingers.’” <emph>Ib.</emph>, 538. <note>(10/10/1769).</note></p>
                    <p>“It is amazing what ignorance of certain points one sometimes finds in men of
                        eminence. A wit about town, who wrote Latin bawdy verses, asked me, how it
                        happened that England and Scotland, which were once two kingdoms, were now
                        one:—and Sir Fletcher Norton did not seem to know that there were such
                        publications as the Reviews.” Johnson, <emph>Ib.</emph>, 546.
                            <note>(16/10/1769). Sir Fletcher Norton was the Speaker of the House of
                            Commons, 1770-80.</note></p>
                    <p><emph>Power of Ennui.</emph> “Mr. Seward,” says Boswell, (<emph>Life of
                            Johnson</emph>, ii, 564 [<emph>sic</emph>], 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> ed.)
                        “has furnished me with a remarkable anecdote. A tradesman who had acquired a
                        large fortune in London retired from business, and went to live at
                        Worcester. His mind being without its usual occupation, and having nothing
                        else to supply its place, preyed upon itself, so that existence was a
                        torment to him. At last he was seized with the stone; and a friend who found
                        him in one of its severest fits, having expressed his concern, No, No, Sir,
                        said he, don’t pity me: what I now feel is ease, compared with that torture
                        of mind from which it relieves me.” <note>546fn. (20/9/1777).</note></p>
                    <p>Mr. Windham, before he set out for Ireland as secretary to the Lord
                        Lieutenant, expressed to Johnson some doubts, “whether he could bring
                        himself to practice those arts which it is supposed a person in that
                        situation has occasion to employ. Don’t be afraid, Sir, said Johnson with a
                        smile, you will soon make a very pretty rascal.” <emph>Ib.</emph>, iii, 453.
                            <note>(12/4/1783).</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap11v" n="11v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“I have heard of a country gentleman, who made a very long and melancholy
                        complaint to the late Duke of Buckingham when he was in great power at
                        court, of several public grievances. The Duke, after having given him a very
                        patient hearing, My dear friend, says he, this is but too true; but I have
                        thought of an expedient which will set all things right, and that very soon.
                        His country friend asked, What it was. You must know, says the Duke, there’s
                        a place of £500 a year fallen this very morning, which I intend to put you
                        in possession of.” Addison’s <emph>Freeholder</emph>, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        17. <note>Addison, <emph>The Free-holder</emph>, pp. 131-2
                            (17/2/1716).</note></p>
                    <p>Two monks (Jesuites) besieged the death bed of Montesquieu, with their pious
                        importunities. The Jesuits were then powerful, and the friends of the
                        sufferer dared not turn them out of the house. They made them dead-drunk,
                        however, a few hours before his death, and sent them then home in that state
                        to their convent. Voltaire, <emph>L’Homme aux 40te Ecus</emph>, p. 84, note.
                                <note><emph>L’homme aux quarante écus</emph>, in
                            <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XLV 84, note 16.</note></p>
                    <p>A fine history of the high character of Tecumseh, an Indian Chief; and an
                        excellent sonnet to his memory. “So liberty he deemed with life was cheaply
                        bought.” Lieut. Hall’s <emph>Travels in Canada and U.S</emph>, p. 229.
                                <note><emph>Travels in Canada and the United States in 1816 and
                                1817.</emph></note></p>
                    <p>A curious fact alledged with respect to the help Sir Isaac Newton received
                        from Barrow, and of the jealousy of his disposition. North’s <emph>Life of
                            Dr. John North</emph>, p. 260. <note>North, <emph>The Life of the
                                Honourable Sir Dudley North … and of the Honourable and Reverend Dr.
                                John North</emph>, pp. 260-1: “Sir Isaac Newton was in the College a
                            Cotemporary, and being made by Nature and Inclination for mathematical
                            Studies, had much Encouragement and Assistance therein from Dr. Barrow,
                            who, as some say, first hinted to him the Plan of his great
                            Cosmographical System. But, however, it falls out oddly that, to the
                            best of my Remembrance, Dr. Barrow is not so much as mentioned in any of
                            his Writings.”</note></p>
                    <p>After Voltaire had written the <emph>Henriade</emph>, and some of his finest
                        theatrical pieces, he was unsuccessful in an attempt to become a member of
                        the Academy. “<hi rend="underline">Gros de Boze</hi> pronounced in a
                        dictatorial tone, that Voltaire should never be one of their dignified
                        members. This de <hi rend="underline">Boze</hi>, whose name is now
                        forgotten, was one of those men, who, with little mind, and not too much
                        knowledge, obtain admission among men of rank and power, and succeed
                        precisely because they neither have the wit to inspire fear, nor to humble
                        the self-love of those who seek the reputation of patronizing men of
                        letters.” [F] Condorcet, <emph>Vie de Voltaire</emph>, p. 21. Whishaw, etc.
                            <note>Condorcet, <emph>La vie de Voltaire</emph>, in Voltaire,
                                <emph>Œuvres</emph>, LXX 21; <emph>The Life of Voltaire</emph>, I
                            52-3. Mill’s reference is to John Wishaw, 1764-1840, the ‘Pope of
                            Holland House.’ Wishaw, in private, expressed himself in a letter to a
                            friend, in such a way as to entirely justify Mill’s opinion: “I am
                            afraid that {<emph>The History of British India</emph>} , although a
                            useful library book, it is far from being a good history. It seems to be
                            wholly deficient in the tone, temper, and dignity which belong to
                            historical composition.” Earlier in the same letter he admitted that “I
                            have not yet read any part of Mill’s book.” See Elizabeth Seymour,
                                <emph>The “Pope” of Holland House</emph>, 1906, pp. 194-5, Wishaw to
                            Thomas Smith (22/1/1818). Earlier reference was to the academician (from
                            1715) Claude Gros de Boze (1680-1753), author of <emph>Le livre
                                jaune</emph>, 1748.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch4scrap12v" n="12v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“Maupertuis, [a man of much wit, but not of too much learning, and of still
                        less philosophy] was tormented by that desire of fame which makes us choose
                        trifling means when the great are wanting, utter paradoxes when we are
                        unable to discover truths, generalise formula when we cannot invent them,
                        and accumulate incongruities when we are deficient in new ideas.” [F]
                        Condorcet, <emph>Vie de Voltaire</emph>, p. 70. <note><emph>Vie de
                                Voltaire</emph>, pp. 70-1; <emph>The Life of Voltaire</emph>, I 188.
                            12v is in a later hand than 12r, and is similar to 11v. The material on
                            12r has been removed to the following section.</note></p>
                    <p>“But after the death of that monarch he (Voltaire) dared to be just to his
                        memory, at the instant in which nearly the whole nation seemed happy in
                        wounding his name. It has been remarked that the philosophers whom Louis XV
                        did not patronize, were at that time the only persons who observed some
                        impartiality; while the priests, loaden with his benefactions, insulted his
                        weaknesses.” [F] <emph>Ib.</emph>, p. 143. <note><emph>Vie</emph>, p. 143;
                                <emph>Life</emph>, I 394.</note></p>
                    <p>Men of eminence, risen from poverty—most of the great benefactors of mankind:
                        Socrates, Virgil, Horace, Columbus, Cooke, Cervantes, Milton, Locke,
                        Copernicus, Erasmus, Luther. <note>This is in a <emph>much</emph> later hand
                            from the material on <ref target="cpb4ch4scrap9r">9r</ref> above, from
                            possibly 1825 or later.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch5" n="5" type="chapter">
                <head>Blackguard Reporters</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch5scrap12r" n="12r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Speaking of blackguard reporters, who had been uncivil to a new comer, A said
                        he would be remarkably obliging to them, B said he should not think himself
                        bound to be very solicitous on that account. A replied, it was necessary,
                        and wise <del>so to act</del> with persons among whom one must act. B said
                        it <del>was a false view of interest</del> looked a sneaking policy to
                            <del>offer</del> pay court as the recompense of insult. It offered a
                        triumph to a base mind, as the offspring of fear. A said that he would
                        continue to oblige them, because he despised their insults. B replied that
                        he would be civil to them, because he would despise them too much to resent
                        their insults; but he would make a distinction between his insulters and his
                        friends. He would do nothing to disoblige them, but he would study to confer
                        his benefits on worthy objects. He would account it mean to pay court where
                        he was insulted; for though it is magnanimous to return good for evil, yet a
                        distinction is to be made between our friends, and our enemies; and between
                        the worthy and the unworthy. In shewing our superiority to the insults of
                        the base by neglect; it is necessary not to give them encouragement, and
                        triumph, by appearing to be afraid of them, and to court them on account of
                        the evil they may do us. In studying to conciliate the good will of all, it
                        is necessary to avoid a weak passiveness, which looks like fear; which can
                        pocket the injury, and immediately squeeze the hand that offers it, that
                        next time it may receive from it a boon.</p>
                    <p>NB Try always to catch the plausible colour the antagonist wishes to hold
                        forth, and shew that while he clothes himself with that, he is at the same
                        time covered with another abominable colour. In affecting to be generous,
                        take care you are not dishonest. In affecting to be very firm in a
                        negotiation, take care you are not petulant and offensive. In affecting to
                        be very mild, take care you are not tame. In affecting to be very bold, take
                        care you are not rash; to be very vigorous, that you are not violent, etc.
                            <note>This item originally had square brackets around it, now removed,
                            to separate it from the material of <ref target="cpb4ch4scrap11v"
                                >11v</ref> and <ref target="cpb4ch4scrap12v">12v</ref>. The section
                            is in an early hand like that of <ref target="cpb4ch1scrap1r">1r</ref>,
                            c. 1802-06? Mill’s remarks may be a reflection of his experience as a
                            reporter for the St. James’s Chronicle from late 1802 to 1807. See Bain,
                            pp. 52-5, who misdates Mill’s role in the paper to 1805-07.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch6" n="6" type="chapter">
                <head>Journal</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch6scrap13r" n="13r" type="scrap">
                    <p>July 12. Was told by a friend that a lady of rank and a courtier told him she
                        had been visited by another lady of the same description, who after the
                        first salutation, exclaimed, I hope you are violent against the queen! This
                        is the spirit of Aristocracy in its perfection: Side with the strong, and
                        please them by crushing the weak. Whatever he desires, who has good and evil
                        to distribute, be foremost in adopting his passions; and shew the most
                        intense ardour for their gratification. The Lord Chancellor [Eldon] said,
                        two nights I think ago, when Liverpool explained the plan of proceedings
                        against the queen, that he wished every body would preserve his mind
                        impartial on this subject, in which the very existence of the country was
                        involved: that in their lordship’s house <del>they possessed</del> this
                        noble virtue was preserved; but <del>without</del> except within the walls
                        of parliament, there where all the virtue of the nation was enclosed,
                            <del>it was grievous to see</del> it was lost. His chancellorship meant
                        by impartiality, partiality all on the right side. The difference between
                        those within and those without the walls of virtue’s manhouse is—that those
                        within have all their partiality for the strong side, those without for the
                        weak. It is very dreadful, say the aristocrats, to see how this dispute
                        about the queen lessens the respect for dignity. Shoemakers and taylors
                        speak of the king and queen, and their quarrels, as if they were men and
                        women! This is very terrible; for if they do not reverence kings, still less
                        will they reverence lords! It is very necessary for the reverence to lords,
                        that there should be a head lord, a first-rate idol—the more of reverence
                        there is paid to him, the more of reverence will be paid to those nearest
                        him—his ministers, and favourites, etc. It is good to observe the interests
                        which aristocrats have in eulogizing kingship. Kingship is one of the
                        instruments by which the fraud is to be carried on. It is one of the best
                        contrivances for the support of the fantom, spurious dignity. <note>The
                            reference is to George IV’s divorce case against Queen Caroline,
                            1768-1821. For Eldon’s remarks see the Debate of 10/6/1820 in the House
                            of Lords on the Queen’s trial, <emph>The Times</emph>, 11/6/1820, p. 2c.
                            The case occasioned great public turmoil, and was a <emph>cause
                                célèbre</emph> for the Whig opposition. Mill’s friend, Henry
                            Brougham, was Queen Caroline’s counsel.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch7" n="7" type="chapter">
                <head>Progress of Knowledge</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch7scrap15r" n="15r" type="scrap">
                    <p>“What has assured, hastened the revolution, is what the ministers never
                        wished to see, that is, that the state of men and their relations with each
                        other has changed. Formerly one governed the people easily because the
                        ministries had a great superiority in intelligence; that superiority was
                        lost to the extent that the level of knowledge of the people was raised, and
                        at last the time came when the nations had become more enlightened than the
                        ministries. It is evident that then one is on the point of a completely
                        different manner of governing, that is what the ministers have not sensed.”
                        [F] <emph>Mémoires de Bailly</emph>, t. i, pp. 250, 251. <note>Bailly,
                                <emph>Mémoires d’un témoin de la révolution.</emph> The title and
                            the first paragraph are in a very early hand (1804?).</note></p>
                    <p>All these classes of persons who <del>desire</del> have an interest in the
                        thraldom of mankind, that is, an interest in deceiving them, (by deception
                        only can thraldom exist) have an interest in resisting the progress of
                        knowledge—an interest in the stupidity, and mental weakness of men—The more
                        contradictory and unsettled men’s notions of right and wrong, of truth and
                        falsehood, the more easy it will be to deceive them, as to what in matters
                        of law or government is just or unjust—noxious or salutary. <note>This
                            paragraph is in a hand like that to be found at the bottom of <ref
                                target="cpb4ch4scrap10r">10r</ref> (1812-15?).</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch8" n="8" type="chapter">
                <head>Imagination and Feeling</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch8scrap32r" n="32r" type="scrap">
                    <p>“If I was la Fontaine, and if madame du Châtelet had the misfortune of being
                        only Madame de Montespan, I would make for her a long epistle in verse, […]
                        but one must pay to the superiority of her mind a tribute which verse never
                        well handles. Verse is not the language of reason, nor of true esteem, nor
                        of respect, nor of friendship.” [F] M. de Voltaire à M. [Nicolas-Claude]
                        Thiriot, <emph>Recueil des Lettres</emph>, Let. clxxxii. <note>(1/3/1736),
                            in Voltaire, <emph>Œuvres</emph>, LII 364. Title and paragraph in a very
                            early hand. Between 37v and 38r that follow, two pages have been torn
                            out, one of which clearly had some writing on it.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch9" n="9" type="chapter">
                <head>Innovations</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap41r" n="41r" type="scrap">
                    <p>A proposal was made to abolish the barbarous <emph>droit d’aubaine</emph> in
                        France. The measure was zealously opposed by the Chancellor d’Aguesseau;
                        because, said he, the <emph>droit d’aubaine</emph> is one of the most
                        ancient laws of the monarchy. This argument prevailed for a while. Voltaire,
                            <emph>Essai sur les Mœurs, etc.</emph>, v. 4, p. 356. <note><emph>Essai
                                sur les mœurs</emph>, note 16, c. 97, in Voltaire,
                                <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XIX 355. The <emph>droit d’aubaine</emph> was
                            the reversion to the crown of the estate of a non-naturalized alien.
                            After the title and first item, which are in an early hand, the hand
                            varies.</note></p>
                    <p>Mankind are obstinately attached to the practices of their forefathers
                        exactly in proportion to their immersion in barbarity. “A firm attachment to
                        the customs of their ancestors” (says Mr. Park, <emph>Travels in
                            Africa</emph>, p. 62) “makes the Africans view with an eye of prejudice
                        every thing that looks like innovation.” <note>Mungo Park, <emph>Travels in
                                the Interior Districts of Africa</emph>, 1799, p. 62, c. 4, 2<hi
                                rend="sup">nd</hi> last ¶.</note></p>
                    <p>“For empires, as for individuals, nothing persists in the same state. Thus
                        the art of government is not that of following the same line, but of varying
                        its course according to the circumstances.” [F] [C.F.C.] Volney,
                            <emph>Considerations sur la guerre actuelle des Turcs</emph>, 1788, p.
                        64, [London].</p>
                    <p>The antiquity of any rule, if there is no other reason for it, is a
                        presumption against it. It must have been made in an age when reason was in
                        its infancy; of which ignorance was the characteristic, deprived of the
                        benefit of experience. Old rules, so far from having experience on their
                        side, have experience against them. By a perverted use of the word
                        experience, they are said to have experience on their side, because men have
                        long witnessed their effects. In the same way, let us suppose that children
                        make rules for their individual lives, which they stiffly adher to till old
                        age and death, and insist for that reason that they are guided by
                        experience, not by speculation—because they are guided by rules, made by
                        antiquity, and of which they have long observed the effects. Would this be
                        to be guided by experience? Would it not be to be guided by something
                        directly contrary to experience? In the spirit of this maxim, ignorance
                        gives law to knowledge, immaturity to maturity, inexperience to experience.
                        This is to live under the tyranny of dead men, legislating for a state of
                        things of which the conception could never have presented itself to their
                        minds. <note>The hand from the middle of 41r to 44r is that of the 1810s to
                            mid-1820s.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap41v" n="41v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“It is in the nature of human laws to be subject to all the accidents which
                        can happen, and to vary in proportion as the will of man changes.” [F]
                            <emph>Esp. des Lois</emph>, lib. XXVI, ch. 2. <note><emph>L’esprit des
                                lois</emph>; in Montesquieu, <emph>Œuvres</emph>, II 751; <emph>The
                                Spirit of the Laws</emph>, p. 59.</note></p>
                    <p>“Is the evil of changing constantly less than that of suffering?” [F]
                            <emph>Ibid., l.</emph> XXIX, ch. 18. <note><emph>Œuvres</emph>, II 882;
                            tr., p. 170.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">Once wrong and always wrong</hi>—such is the motto of
                        all non-innovation votaries.</p>
                    <p>“As in the natural body a fever often leads to a renewal of the constitution,
                        so still more in the political, advantageous establishments commonly owe
                        their very conception to violent disorders.” Mitford, <emph>Hist. of
                            Greece</emph>, v. I, ch. 5 [<emph>sic</emph>], Sect. 2. <note><emph>The
                                History of Greece</emph>, I 292, c. 4, § 3, 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>
                            ¶.</note></p>
                    <p>Another candid observation, by the same author.—“It is a remark of J.J.
                        Rousseau, that the many plans of government proposed by speculative men,
                        however excellent in theory, are generally slighted as mere visions,
                        impossible to be reduced to practice: but says the philosopher very justly,
                        had Lycurgus been a legislator in speculation only, his scheme would have
                        appeared much more visionary than Plato’s.” Mitford, <emph>ubi supra.</emph>
                        <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, 327, fn. 24.</note></p>
                    <p>It has been made a question whether a man could be a good citizen, and yet
                        both desire, and labour for, the change of the constitution. If any other
                        body could doubt about the affirmative, Mr. Mitford at least does not.
                        Praising Socrates for not liking the Athenian democracy, he praises him, for
                        desiring to see it altered, and lending his efforts to procure its
                        alteration—“Though Socrates was a good and faithful subject of the Athenian
                        government, and would promote no sedition, no political violence, yet he
                        could not like the Athenian constitution. He wished for wholesome changes by
                        gentle means; and it seems even to have been a principal object of the
                        labours to which he dedicated himself, to infuse principles into the rising
                        generation, that might bring about the desirable change insensibly.”
                        Mitford’s <emph>Greece</emph>, ch. xxii, § 3. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, V
                            150.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap42r" n="42r" type="scrap">
                    <p>When a diminution is made of liberty, the word innovation is never sounded—it
                        is only when a proposal is made to increase it.</p>
                    <p>“If a great change is to be made in human affairs, the minds of men will be
                        fitted to it; the general opinions and feelings will draw that way. Every
                        fear, every hope will forward it; and they who persist in opposing this
                        mighty current in human affairs, will appear rather to resist the decrees of
                        Providence itself, than the mere designs of men. They will not be resolute
                        and firm, but perverse and obstinate.” Burke’s <emph>Works</emph>, v. 7, p.
                        85. <emph>Thoughts on French Affairs</emph> written in 1791. (See second
                        paragraph below.) <note>Sentence in brackets added later in a different ink,
                            probably put in when the second Burke item was added.</note></p>
                    <p>Ought government to be adapted to circumstances and manners—or ought it not?
                        If it ought—then innovation is unavoidable.—It is a good observation I have
                        met with somewhere, I think in <emph>Memoires de Bailly</emph>, that
                        formerly the nobless and clergy were the natural governors in every country
                        in Europe, because they were then the most instructed. Now a middle rank has
                        sprung [up], in which is found the greatest share of knowledge. What a
                        difference is this by nature calculated to produce? “The better nature,”
                        says Burke somewhere, “ought ever to preside.” “Soul, considered
                        collectively, has the care of all that which is considered soulless.” [G]
                        Platonis, <emph>Phaedr.</emph>, p. 1221. <note>Bailly, <emph>Mémoires d’un
                                témoin de la révolution</emph>, I 250-1; see <ref
                                target="cpb4ch7scrap15r">15r</ref>. Plato, <emph>Phædrus</emph>,
                                246<hi rend="sup">b</hi>, Loeb 473. Burke reference not
                            located.</note></p>
                    <p>(See second paragraph above.) “A silent revolution in the moral world
                        preceded the political, and prepared it. … It was no longer the <hi
                            rend="underline">great</hi> and the <hi rend="underline">populace</hi>.
                        … The middle classes had swelled far beyond their former proportion. … These
                        were all the energies by which fortune is acquired; these the consequences
                        of their success. … The press, in reality, has made every government, in its
                        spirit, almost democratic.” Burke’s <emph>Works</emph>, v. 8<hi rend="sup"
                            >th</hi>, p. 185.—It follows by Burke’s own doctrine that to fight
                        against the changes which have now become necessary, is to fight against the
                        decrees of Providence. <note><emph>Letters on the Regicide Peace</emph>, n.
                            II, in <emph>Works</emph>, VIII 259-60.</note></p>
                    <p>“Knowledge, which in the two last centuries either did not exist at all or
                        existed solidly … in chosen hands, was now diffused. … General wealth
                        loosened morals, relaxed vigilance, and increased presumption. … When it was
                        once discovered by the revolution in France that a struggle between
                        establishment and rapacity could be maintained, though but for one year, and
                        in one place, I was sure that a practicable breach was made in the whole</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap42v" n="42v" type="scrap">
                    <p>order of things and in every country. … Authority could not stand upon
                        authority alone. … Situations formerly supported persons. It now became
                        necessary that personal qualities should support situations. Formerly, where
                        authority was found, wisdom and virtue were presumed. But now the veil was
                        torn.” Burke, <emph>Letter to Wm. Elliot Esq., Works</emph>, v. 7, p. 313,
                        314. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, VII 363-4.</note></p>
                    <p>Burke says, that when he dissuaded the people from innovating, he persuaded
                        himself that the hands in which authority was placed would be voluntarily
                        employed in Reformation. … “What a base and foolish thing,” he cries, “is it
                        for any consolidated body of authority to say, or to act as if it said, ‘I
                        will put my trust not in my own virtue, but in your patience; I will indulge
                        in effeminacy, in indolence, in corruption; I will give way to all my
                        perverse and vitious humours, because you cannot punish me without the
                        hazard of ruining yourselves?’—… I was indeed well aware that power rarely
                        reforms itself. […] But I was in hopes that provident fear might prevent
                        fruitless penitence. I trusted that danger might produce at least
                        circumspection; I flattered myself in a moment like this that nothing would
                        be added to make authority top heavy; that the very moment of an earthquake
                        would not be the time chosen for adding a story to our houses. … I do not
                        repent that I thought better of those to whom I wished well, than they will
                        suffer me long to think that they deserved.” <emph>Ibid.</emph>, p. 314,
                        315. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, 364-5.</note></p>
                    <p>“I am not of opinion that the race of men, and the commonwealths they create,
                        like the bodies of individuals, grow effete. … These analogies between
                        bodies natural and politic, though they may sometimes illustrate arguments,
                        furnish no arguments of themselves. They are but too often used under the
                        colour of a specious philosophy, to find apologies for the despair of
                        laziness and pusillanimity, and to excuse the want of all manly efforts,
                        when the exigencies of our country call for them the more loudly.—How often
                        has public calamity been arrested on the very brink of ruin</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap43r" n="43r" type="scrap">
                    <p>by the seasonable energy of a single man! Have we no such man amongst us? I
                        am as sure as I am of my being, that one vigorous mind without office,
                        without situation, without public functions of any kind (at a time when the
                        want of such a thing is felt, as I am sure it is) I say, one such man,
                        confiding in the aid of God, and full of just reliance in his own fortitude,
                        vigour, enterprise and perseverance, would first draw to him some few like
                        himself, and then that multitudes, hardly thought to be in existence, would
                        appear and troop about him. … It is not a hazarded assertion, it is a great
                        truth, that when once things are gone out of their ordinary course, it is by
                        acts out of the ordinary course they can alone be re-established. Republican
                        spirit can only be combated by a spirit of the same nature. … I would
                        persuade a resistance both to the corruption and to the reformation that
                        prevails. … A victory over real corruptions would enable us to baffle the
                        spurious and pretended reformations. … I would wish to call the impulses of
                        individuals at once to the aid and to the controul of authority. By this,
                        which I call the true republican spirit, paradoxical as it may appear,
                        monarchies alone can be rescued from the imbecility of courts and the
                        madness of the crowd. This republican spirit would not suffer men in high
                        place to bring ruin on their country and on themselves. It would reform, not
                        by destroying, but by saving, the great, the rich and the powerful. … The
                        great must submit to the dominion of prudence and virtue, or none will long
                        submit to the dominion of the great.—I well know that every thing of the
                        daring kind which I speak of is critical—but the times are critical. New
                        things in a new world! I see no hopes in the common tracks. If men are not
                        to be found who can be got to feel within them an impulse—</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap43v" n="43v" type="scrap">
                    <p><hi rend="center"><emph>quod neques monstrare, et sentio
                        tantum</emph>,</hi></p>
                    <p>[which I cannot demonstrate and only feel] and which makes them impatient of
                        the present; if more can be got to feel that private persons may sometimes
                        assume that sort of magistracy which does not depend on the nomination of
                        kings, or the election of the people, but has an inherent and self existent
                        power which both would recognize; I see nothing in the world to hope.”
                            <emph>Ibid.</emph>, pp. 316 to 321. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>,
                            366-71.</note></p>
                    <p>“I have ever abhorred, since the first dawning of my understanding to this
                        its obscure twilight, all the operations of opinion, fancy, inclination and
                        will, in the affairs of government, where only a sovereign reason, paramount
                        to all forms of legislation and administration, should dictate. Government
                        is made for the very purpose of opposing that reason to will and to caprice,
                        in the reformers or in the reformed, in the governors or in the governed, in
                        kings, in senates, or in people.” Burke’s <emph>Works</emph>, v. 7, p. 393,
                            <emph>Letter to a Noble Lord.</emph>
                        <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, VIII 23-4.</note></p>
                    <p>There is a class of politicians, composed of courtiers, priests, and lawyers,
                        place and pension holders and hunters, and all those who are the dupes of
                        their false pretences, who hold up every extension of legal benefits to the
                        great body of the people, as pregnant with mischief; live or affect to live
                        in a state of perpetual alarm with respect to the people; who are persuaded
                        or desire to appear persuaded that the people are ready to swallow them up;
                        who on every attempt of the people to express a will, or to use the means
                        for carrying their will into effect, desire to crush that attempt in the
                        embryo. These persons represent us as living in a state of society in which
                        there is an active and deadly struggle between the two great classes of the
                        Community, the people with authority and the people without; that the first
                        can be safe by no other means than by keeping down the latter. Do they think
                        that this is a state of society that can last? Is this a struggle that can
                        be perpetual? Were light in any, but the smallest degree, <del>a
                            companion</del> a visitant to their eyes, this is a question</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap44r" n="44r" type="scrap">
                    <p>which could not fail to stare them with an awful countenance. As surely as
                        they are in existence it is a struggle which cannot last. Government rests
                        on opinion. Who is ignorant of this universal maxim? The terrors of these
                        people never cease proclaiming that the foundation of opinion with respect
                        to our government is gone. If that be really the case the government must go
                        after it. The only preventive which the course of things provides, or of
                        which the order of things admits, is to recover the opinion. Is that what
                        these people are in the way to compass? It is the very reverse.</p>
                    <p>It will be allowed that England has been progressive—Vast are the changes
                        which we have undergone since the days of Henry VII. These changes have,
                        most of them, been for the
                        better—wealth—manners—enjoyments—arts—sciences—etc., etc. Then it follows
                        that a plan of governnent, good for the time of Henry VII would not be a
                        plan good for the present times.—“Nothing in progression,” says Burke, “can
                        rest on its original plan. We may as well think of rocking a grown man in
                        the cradle of an infant.” <emph>Letter to the Sheriffs of
                            Bristol—Works</emph>, 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> Ed., p. 143. <note><emph>A
                                Letter from Mr. Burke to the Sheriffs of Bristol, on the Affairs of
                                America, ibid.</emph>, III 189.</note></p>
                    <p>The following a fine example of the irresistible force, and never ceasing
                        agency of innovation. At the beginning of the preface to Baron Gilbert’s
                            <emph>Common pleas</emph>, the Editors of that work say—“At the
                        institution of the Court of Common Pleas (as well as all the other courts of
                        justice) there was established a sure method or form of practice. … This”
                        (the experience of certain inconveniencies) “obliged the <hi
                            rend="underline">Justices</hi> of the court to regulate and amend the
                        practice in many points, as they saw occasion; nay even the Legislature have
                        sometimes been forced to interpose their authority to put a stop to and
                        remedy such mischiefs as occurred in the practice. Thus by several
                        regulations and amendments almost <hi rend="underline">every branch</hi> of
                        the method or form of practice, which was at first established, <hi
                            rend="underline">is in a great measure inverted; and the present method
                            or form of practice so essentially differs</hi> from the former, that
                        the original intent of its institution is with great difficulty to be
                        attained to.” <note>Sir Geoffrey Gilbert, <emph>The History and Practice of
                                Civil Actions Particularly in the Court of Common Pleas</emph>,
                            1761, pp. iii-iv of the Preface.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap44v" n="44v" type="scrap">
                    <p>The abolition of the Star Chamber was an innovation, not only very great, but
                        which Hume says, it was natural in that age to regard as something
                        altogether untried, and unspeakably hazardous. <emph>Hist. of Eng.</emph>,
                        v. 6, p. 420. <note><emph>The History of England</emph>, VI 421, c.
                            54.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Innovation admired by Blackstone</hi>. “And here I cannot but
                        again admire the wisdom of suffering time to bring to perfection new
                        remedies, more easy and beneficial to the subject.” Blackstone,
                            <emph>Comment.</emph>, B. 3, ch. 24, v. 3, p. 390. The occasion is—the
                        superseding attaint of a jury, by the practice of granting new trials.
                                <note><emph>Commentaries</emph>, III 389.</note></p>
                    <p>There are two ways in which Antiquity may be followed. One of these ways is
                        good. The other evil. Antiquity may be followed, so far as the
                        inconveniences of change, and the advantages of keeping things in their
                        ordinary course, extend. It may be followed, <hi rend="underline"
                            >merely</hi> from a blind attachment, merely because it is antiquity: it
                        may be followed from an interested motive, either because it would be
                        troublesome to make a change, or because it would put a stop to some private
                        profit. The former is good, the latter is bad. The object in each case is to
                        study what of real advantage would remain by leaving things as they are—what
                        of real advantage would be gained by making chan[g]e—and so to do what will
                        afford the greatest advantage.</p>
                    <p>“All human institutions are liable to abuse, and require continual
                        amendments, which are, in reality, so many alterations. It is not indeed
                        possible to make a law which does not innovate, more or less, in the
                        government.” Hume, <emph>Hist.</emph>, v. 8, p. 14. <note><emph>The History
                                of England</emph>, c. 66.</note></p>
                    <p>If “no innovation,” be the indefeasible rule of wisdom, why not make a law
                        rending it criminal to oppose any? NB Push this idea. Consult Hume,
                            <emph>Hist.</emph>, v. 8, pp. 13, 14, where [there] is an account of and
                        a criticism on, such a <emph>projet de loi.</emph>
                        <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, 12-14. A “new bill was introduced into the house
                            of peers [in 1675]. … All members of either house, and all who possessed
                            any office, were by this bill required to swear, that it was not lawful
                            upon any pretence whatsoever, to take arms against the king; … and that
                            they will not at any time endeavour the alteration of the protestant
                            religion, or of the established government either in church or state. …
                            There were many other absurdities in this text, particularly that of
                            binding men by oath not to alter the government either in church or
                            state; since all human institutions are liable to abuse, and require
                            continual amendments, which are, in reality, so many alterations. It is
                            not indeed possible to make a law, which does not innovate, more or
                            less, in the government.”</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch9scrap45r" n="45r" type="scrap">
                    <p>To oppose innovation is—<emph>pro tanto</emph>, to make society stationary—to
                        exclude improvement. No innovation in Sicily for many ages—Happy Sicily!
                            <note>This last paragraph is in the larger, shakier hand of the
                            mid-1820s on. Two pages have been removed between both 52v and 53r, and
                            59v and 60r.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch10" n="10" type="chapter">
                <head>Popular Impressions</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch10scrap60r" n="60r" type="scrap">
                    <lg>
                        <l>Man’s credulous, and by his wavering mind</l>
                        <l>All is received; it is a clay refined;</l>
                        <l>With ease impressed, what strongest will appear</l>
                        <l>Is dire surprise or unexpected fear. [F]</l>
                        <l>Voltaire, <emph>La Pucelle D’Orleans</emph>, Chant 4me. <note><emph>La
                                    pucelle d’Orléans</emph>, canto 4, in <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XI
                                80; <emph>Works</emph>, XX-1, p. 137. Title and first paragraph of
                                this section in a very early hand (1802?); rest of material in an
                                early, <emph>c.</emph> 1803-06, hand.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <p>“When objects are imperfectly seen, they easily take forms from the
                        imagination.” Johnson, <emph>Life of Rowe.</emph> NB Ignorant men naturally
                        timid. <note>In <emph>Works</emph>, X 63.</note></p>
                    <p><lg>
                            <l>Who would believe what strange bugbears</l>
                            <l>Mankind creates itself, of fears,</l>
                            <l>That spring, like fern, that insect weed,</l>
                            <l>Equivocally, without seed.</l>
                            <l>And leave no possible foundation</l>
                            <l>But merely in th’imagination!</l>
                            <l>And yet can do more dreadful feats</l>
                            <l>Than hags, with all their imps and teats;</l>
                            <l>Make more bewitch and haunt themselves,</l>
                            <l>Than all their nurseries of elves.</l>
                            <l>For fear does things so like a witch,</l>
                            <l>’Tis hard t’unriddle which is which.</l>
                            <l>… …</l>
                            <l>Men, [<emph>sic</emph> And] when they neither see nor hear,</l>
                            <l>Have more than both supply’d by fear,</l>
                            <l>That makes them in the dark see visions,</l>
                            <l>And hag themselves with apparitions;</l>
                            <l>And when their eyes discover least</l>
                            <l>Discern the subtlest objects best. <note>Butler,
                                        <emph>Hudibras</emph>, P. III, Canto III, ll. 1-12,
                                    17-22.</note></l>
                        </lg></p>
                    <p>“They readily discerned that human life is swayed by two great tyrants, hope
                        and fear, and that a man who could use both of these to advantage would
                        speedily enrich himself.” [G] Luciani, <emph>Pseudomantis</emph>, p. 215, §
                        8. <note><emph>Alexander the False Prophet</emph>, in Lucian,
                                <emph>Opera</emph>, II 215, Loeb 185.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch10scrap60v" n="60v" type="scrap">
                    <lg>
                        <l>There needs no other charm, nor conjurer,</l>
                        <l>To raise infernal spirits up, but fear;</l>
                        <l>That makes men pull their horns in like a snail,</l>
                        <l>That’s both a prisoner to itself, and gaol;</l>
                        <l>Draws more fantastic shapes than in the grains,</l>
                        <l>Of knotted wood, in some mens crazy brains,</l>
                        <l>When all the cocks they think they see, and bulls,</l>
                        <l>Are only in the insides of their skulls.</l>
                        <l>Butler, <emph>Miscel. Thoughts.</emph>
                            <note>In <emph>The Genuine Remains</emph>, I 257-8.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <p><emph>Sunt mobiles ad superstitionem peruculsæ semel mentes.</emph> [“So
                        pliable to superstitions are minds once unbalanced.”] Tacit., <emph>Annal.,
                            l.</emph> I, c. 28. <note>Tacitus, <emph>The Annals</emph>, B. I, c. 28,
                            Loeb 291.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch11" n="11" type="chapter">
                <head>Jottings</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch11scrap68r" n="68r" type="scrap">
                    <p>The character of Lord North, the grandfather of the Lord Keeper Guilford, as
                        drawn by North in the life of Guilford, is a fine picture, of a
                        self-sufficient, tyrannical, vindictive, old man—of the malignant passions,
                        which a <del>fancied superior</del> factitious superiority to other men, and
                        the habitual subservience of other men are calculated to engender in an
                        uncultivated mind. See that <emph>Life</emph>, pp. 36, 40-43. There also is
                        seen a fine specimen of the delicacy of the times. <note><emph>The Life of
                                Francis North</emph>, I 36, 40-3. See <emph>CPB</emph> III <ref
                                target="cpb3ch5scrap143v">143v</ref> for a lengthy quotation of
                            this. The specimen of delicacy is undoubtedly the following on pp. 38-9:
                            “At last he ventured to say, <emph>My lord, what is your pleasure I
                                shall do with these papers</emph>? The old lord stopt short, and
                            turning, said, <emph>wipe</emph> your a—e with them.” See App.
                        I.</note></p>
                    <p><emph>Easily to change one’s opinions</emph>—to be continually on the
                        compromise with opinions—to use opinions, as the gamester uses his counters,
                        to play with, and to gain other people’s money, it is very necessary
                            <emph>to be Superficial.</emph> This important proposition is thus
                        illustrated by Mad. de Stael, (<emph>Rev. Franc.</emph>, iii, 385). “This
                        levity they must have to change parties readily; they must have it not to
                        enter thoroughly into any study, for otherwise it would cost them too much
                        to say the contrary of what they would have seriously learned; general
                        ignorance facilitates confident affirmation. In short, they must have this
                        levity to lavish, from democracy down to legitimacy, from the republic down
                        to military despotism, all the phrases most opposite in point of meaning,
                        but which bear a resemblance to each other, like persons of the same family,
                        equally superficial, disdainful, and calculated never to present but one
                        side of a question in opposition to that which circumstances have rendered
                        common.” [F] <note><emph>La révolution françoise; The French
                                Revolution</emph>, III 362-3, P. VI, c. 10.</note></p>
                    <p><emph>Improvement of Manners in England.</emph> “In the last age when my
                        mother lived in London, there were two sets of people, those who gave the
                        wall, and those who took it; the peaceable and the quarrelsome. When I
                        returned to Litchfield, after having been in London, my mother asked me,
                        whether I was one of those who gave the wall, or those who took it.
                            <emph>Now</emph> it is fixed that every man keeps to the right, or, if
                        one is taking the wall, another yields it, and it is never a dispute.”
                        Johnson, in <emph>Life</emph> by Boswel, i, 87, 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Ed.
                            <note>(1737), Boswell, <emph>Life of Johnson.</emph></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch11scrap68v" n="68v" type="scrap">
                    <p><emph>Want of care about the exact truth.</emph> When it was stated to Dr.
                        Johnson [by Blair in a letter], on the authority of Ld. Bathurst, that
                        Pope’s <emph>Essay on Man</emph> was written by Bolingbroke, and only put
                        into verse by Pope, he said, “Depend upon it, Sir, this is too strongly
                        stated. Pope may have had from Bolingbroke the philosophic stamina of his
                        Essay; […] but the thing is not true in the latitude that Lord Bathurst
                            [<emph>sic</emph> Blair], without intending to falsify, gives room to
                        suppose. […] It is amazing, Sir, what deviations there are from precise
                        truth, in the account which is given of almost every thing. I told Mrs.
                        Thrale, you have so little anxiety about truth, <hi rend="underline">that
                            you never tax your memory with the exact thing</hi>.” <emph>Ib.</emph>,
                        iii, 200. <note>(10/10/1779), first part rather inexactly quoted by Mill.
                            The references are to the first Earl of Bathurst (1684-1755), and to
                            Hugh Blair (1718-1800), the writer on rhetoric.</note></p>
                    <p>“There is a middle state of mind, between conviction and hypocrisy, of which
                        many are conscious.” Johnson, <emph>Ib.</emph>, 378.
                            <note>(3/6/1781).</note></p>
                    <p>Abilities, which are too feeble to do much good, may, with the advantages of
                        place and time, be efficient to do much evil; for example Burke, who could
                        do little to stem the torrent which plunged the nation in the evils of the
                        American war; but <del>enabled</del> strengthened the enemies of the people
                        to do ten times more mischief in fighting against the French Revolution than
                        otherwise they would have been able to do. <note>This paragraph is in a late
                            hand, <emph>c.</emph> 1826 to 1836.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch12" n="12" type="chapter">
                <head>National Characters</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch12scrap76r" n="76r" type="scrap">
                    <lg>
                        <l>You know the ardor of the Gallic host,</l>
                        <l>Those fools who such a fund of honour boast,</l>
                        <l>To battle flying just as to a dance. [F]</l>
                        <l>Voltaire, <emph>Pucelle d’Orleans</emph>, Chant 4<hi rend="sup">eme</hi>.
                                    <note><emph>La pucelle d’Orléans</emph>, Canto 4, in
                                    <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XI 81; <emph>Works</emph>, XX-1, p. 138.
                                Title and text in a very early hand (1802?).</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Exploit quite new to haughty Briton’s feeling</l>
                        <l>More hardy far in feats than double dealing. [F] <emph>Ibid.</emph>, Ch.
                                21<hi rend="sup">me</hi>. <note>Canto 21, <emph>Œuvres</emph>, 380;
                                    <emph>Works</emph>, XX-2, p. 233.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch13" n="13" type="chapter">
                <head>Idola Politica</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch13scrap82r" n="82r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Sources of Misjudgement in matters of Politics—Supplement to Bentham’s
                            <emph>Fausses Manieres de raisonner en matiere de legislation, Traités
                            de Legislation</emph>, t. I, p. 108. <note><emph>Traités de législation
                                civile et pénale</emph>, ed. E. Dumont, I 108-40, c. 13. See
                            Bentham, <emph>The Theory of Legislation</emph>, ed. C.K. Ogden, 1931,
                            pp. 66-87, c. 13 of the “Principles of Legislation.” Bentham lists ten
                            sophisms: 1. Antiquity is not a Reason, 2. The Authority of Religion is
                            not a Reason, 3. Reproach of Innovation is not a Reason, 4. An Arbitrary
                            Definition is not a Reason, 5. Metaphors are not reasons, 6. A Fiction
                            is not a Reason, 7. Fancy is not a Reason, 8. Antipathy and Sympathy are
                            not Reasons, 9. Begging the Question is not a Reason, 10. An imaginary
                            Law is not a Reason. The first three paragraphs of this section are in a
                            pre-1808 hand, the next are probably written shortly after that time,
                            and the remainder in his 1810 to 1825 hand.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">Accidental and improper associations with the love of
                            country</hi>, principally by means of <hi rend="underline">pride of
                            country</hi>. A man loves to exaggerate the glories of his country—hence
                        believes that every thing it does, or has done, is all admirable—the best
                        climate, the best soil; the best government, next, and the best laws—after
                        that prejudice against every man who proposes amendment. True patriotism
                        takes the opposite course—valuing justly all the particulars in which its
                        country excells, it carefully searches out those in which it may excell
                        more, and labours incessantly to bring the improvement about. This a
                        fruitful source of mischief. “And since opinion of store is one of the chief
                        causes of want.” [L] Bacon, <emph>Nov. Org.</emph>, p. 1. <note><emph>The
                                Great Instauration</emph>, in <emph>The Philosophical Works</emph>,
                            p. 243.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">The false influence of Names</hi> may be mentioned as a
                        greater source of error in politics, than perhaps any where else. The term
                            <hi rend="underline">Navigation laws</hi>, for example, consecrates
                        every absurd measure to which it can be applied, the term <hi
                            rend="underline">Constitution</hi> every absurd establishment. The term
                            <hi rend="underline">Jacobin</hi> has lately served to cover with odium
                        every thing or person on whom it could be fixed. The way in which it is
                        employed to refute argument reminds one of the similar use which was made of
                        the word <hi rend="underline">Heretic</hi> by the Jesuits, for example,
                        against Pascal. “You say,” says Pascal to them, <emph>Lettres
                            Provinciales</emph>, Let. 17, “‘all that is necessary to answer my
                        fifteen Letters is to say fifteen times that I am a heretic,’ and that ‘once
                        declared such I do not deserve to be believed by anyone.’” [F] The answer
                        which Pascal makes to the reverend father whom he is addressing, would suit
                        many of the political champions who deal in the argument of calling Jacobin.
                        “You know very well, Father, that such an accusation is so grave that it is
                        intolerable temerity to make it unless it can be proved. What proof do you
                        have? When have I been seen at Charenton? When have I failed to hear mass or
                        carry out the parochial duties of a Christian? When have I acted in concert
                        with heretics or in schism with the Church? What council have I
                        contradicted? What papal constitution have I violated? You must answer,
                        Father, or … you know very well what I mean.” [F] <note>In Pascal,
                                <emph>Œuvres</emph>, p. 454; <emph>The Provincial Letters</emph>,
                            pp. 259-60, Letter 17. See <emph>CPB</emph> III <ref
                                target="cpb3ch4scrap99r">99r</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">Generalization of particular instances</hi>, alias, <hi
                            rend="underline"><del>making</del> erecting a particular precedent into
                            a general rule</hi>, alias, <hi rend="underline">contempt of abstract
                            general rules</hi>.—No precedent can serve as the foundation of a
                        general rule—because no particular case can ever resemble any other
                        particular case—The use of abstraction is, from observing the particulars in
                        which</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch13scrap82v" n="82v" type="scrap">
                    <p><del>a class of</del> all the cases of a class agree, to make a rule which
                        shall approximate as nearly as possible to all the individual cases of the
                        whole class—the approximation in the whole class will thus be in a vast
                        proportion closer than were the rule taken from any individual in the
                        class.—All judge-made law, therefore, decisions founded on mere precedents,
                        extremely imperfect—All political judgements founded on the same ground,
                        marked by infirmity.—This illustrated by well chosen instances might be very
                        useful. Take a thousand copies of an original painting; though all of them
                        may bear great resemblance to the original, few of them will bear much, if
                        any, resemblance to one another. Some good observations in Heineccius
                            (<emph>Elem. Juris.</emph>, Præf., p. ix and x) to the same purpose, and
                        on the propensity of lawyers to generalize individual instances.
                                <note><emph>Elementa juris civilis secundum ordinem
                                pandectarum</emph>, “Praefatio,” in <emph>Opera</emph>, V ix-x, See
                                <emph>CPB</emph> I <ref target="cpb1ch10scrap140r"
                            >140r</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Use and abuse of precedents</hi>.—<hi rend="underline"
                            >Use</hi>, to observe accurately the institutions which have been set up
                        by those who have gone before us, and mark justly the consequences, good or
                        bad, which have flowed from them, taking lessons of imitation from those
                        which have had consequences good upon the whole, and lessons of avoidance
                        from those which have had consequences bad upon the whole.—<hi
                            rend="underline">Abuse</hi>, observing the institutions which have been
                        set up by those before us, but without taking any note of their
                        consequences, one way or another, jumbling them all together in hotchpotch,
                        and taking them in the lump for the rule of action at the present
                        moment.—Idea taken from a manuscript of Bentham. <note>Reference to Bentham
                            unverified. <emph>Possibly</emph> a reference to Bentham’s
                                <emph>Constitutional Code</emph>, B. II, c. 9, § 25, art. 43, in
                                <emph>Collected Works</emph>, IX 322.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Influence</hi>. The placeman’s watch word—the constitution
                        stands upon influence. The <hi rend="underline">equipoise</hi> is its
                        well-begotten child—and what a beautiful thing the equipoise is!—See for a
                        good quotation vituperative, Montesquieu, <emph>Grandeur et Decadence des
                            Romains</emph>, Chap. IV. <note><emph>Considérations sur les causes de
                                la grandeur des romains, et de leur décadence</emph>, c. 4, in
                                <emph>Œuvres</emph>, II 84; <emph>Reflexions on the Causes of the
                                Rise and Fall of the Roman Empire</emph>, pp. 27-8. There is an
                            extended parallel between Carthage and Rome which fits Mill’s
                            description and in the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ¶ an attack on favorites:
                            “The advantage of a free state is, that it admits of no favourites; but
                            when the contrary is seen, and instead of the friends and relations of a
                            prince, great fortunes are amassed for the friends and relations of all
                            persons who have any share in the government; in this case an universal
                            ruin must ensue; the laws are then eluded more dangerously, than they
                            are infringed by a sovereign prince, who being always the greatest
                            citizen in the state, is most concerned to labour at its
                            preservation.”</note></p>
                    <p>“For nothing is so mischievous as the apotheosis of error; and it is a very
                        plague of the understanding for vanity to become the object of veneration.”
                        [L] Bacon; <emph>Nov. Org., l.</emph> I, Aphor. 65. <note><emph>Novum
                                organum</emph>, in <emph>The Philosophical Works</emph>, p.
                            272.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch14" n="14" type="chapter">
                <head>War</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch14scrap87r" n="87r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Remarking the little skill displayed by the republican generals in Africa
                        against Cesar, compared with the astonishing resources brought forth by that
                        incomparable general, Guischardt observes, “If one considers that these old
                        warriors of the Republican party had all served for a long time in the same
                        armies with Caesar, one would be obliged to admit, that routine and
                        experience, in the skills of war, go for little without the help of study
                        and genius.” [F] Guischardt, <emph>Memoires Militaires</emph>, t. ii, p.
                        217. <note>K.G. Guischardt, <emph>Mémoires militaires sur les Grecs et les
                                Romains … et l’analyse de la campagne de Jules César en
                                Afrique</emph>, The Hague 1758, II 217, c. 10. First paragraph of
                            this section in a very early hand (1802?), second and third in an early
                            hand (pre-1810?), remaining c. 1810-1825.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline">Defects of a monarchy in regard to War</hi>. “In
                        monarchies, the nobility and great men fill the court with intrigues, where
                        men of merit and probity seldom have the advantage, which greatly weakens
                        the operations of monarchs.—There is as little unity here as in
                        democracies;—a great sense of danger can only calm the storm which agitates
                        the state, and make room for the able pilot; but no sooner does the tempest
                        subside than he is removed and replaced by some insignificant favourite. So
                        that this government, which should be strong from its principle of unity, is
                        in fact weak and fluctuating, as the characters of the favourites, who
                        rapidly succeed to each other, differ. Their wars, when carried into distant
                        countries, are without plan or vigour;—parry only the first impetuosity,
                        their efforts will successively diminish, and at length vanish entirely.”
                            <emph>Continuation of the late war in Germany</emph>, Part ii, by
                        Major-General Lloyd, P. iii, ch. 3. <note>H.H.E. Lloyd, <emph>Continuation
                                of the History of the Late War in Germany</emph>, 1781, v. II, t.
                            II, P. III, c. 3, pp. 113-14. Henry Humphrey Evans Lloyd, 1720-83,
                            distinguished himself in various European armies, and wrote a series of
                            historical works at the end of his life.</note></p>
                    <p>“A <hi rend="underline">democracy</hi> is of all governments the best
                        calculated for a <hi rend="underline">defensive</hi>, the least for an <hi
                            rend="underline">offensive</hi> war.” <emph>Ibid.</emph>, ch. 4.
                                <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, c. 4, p. 115.</note></p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>O direful war! of Death the sister dread!</l>
                        <l>The cut-throat’s right, or heroes’, as ’tis said;</l>
                        <l>Thou monster bloody from the loins derived</l>
                        <l>Of Atropos: how have thy crimes deprived</l>
                        <l>This earth of souls? ’tis thou inspirest those fears.</l>
                        <l>Wide spreading devastation, blood, and tears. [F]</l>
                        <l>Voltaire, <emph>Pucelle</emph>, Chant 19<hi rend="sup">me</hi>.
                                    <note><emph>La Pucelle d’Orléans</emph>, Canto 19, in
                                    <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XI 347;. <emph>Works</emph>, XX-2, p.
                                97.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <p>“Marshal Saxe calls battles the resource of ignorant generals; ‘when they do
                        not know what to do they give battle.’” General Lloyd, <emph>War in
                            Germany</emph>, Preface. <note>Lloyd, <emph>Continuation of the History
                                of the Late War in Germany</emph>, v. II, t. II, Preface, p.
                            xxxi.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch14scrap87v" n="87v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“The greater part of generals win battles in order to give employment to the
                        couriers who were to carry the news of their victories, it is rare that they
                        draw solid results from these victories. … Each party attributes to himself
                        either the victory itself or the reality of the victory. … The true means to
                        determine these disputes would be to act as conquerors after the battle. … A
                        general who gains a victory the whole profit of which is for the dealers in
                        crepes and blackcloth, is found in every country.” [F] Bayle,
                            <emph>Diction.</emph>, Art. Cesar, Rem. B. <note>“César,” in
                                <emph>Dictionnaire</emph>, I 876-7. Mill has drawn the quotation
                            from parts of note B and the text.</note></p>
                    <p>Montecuculi said there were three things necessary in war. The first was
                        money—the second was money—the third money. <note>Count General Raimondo
                            Montecuccoli, <emph>Commentaires sur les mémoires de Montecuculi par M.
                                le Comte Turpin de Crisse</emph>, Paris 1769, I 307, B. I, c. 2,
                            art. 5.</note></p>
                    <p>“An author once read to Aurungzebe a long account of one of his battles with
                        Dara Shekkoh. The emperor observed at the conclusion, that he must certainly
                        have been upon a high mountain during the engagement, which he had seen so
                        minutely, as he himself, though commanding the line, and mounted on an
                        elephant, did not perceive one third of the particulars he had described.”
                            <emph>Memoirs of Eradut Khan</emph>, p. 93. After a battle is begun it
                        is impossible for a single person to see more of the operations than those
                        which take place near himself. <note>Iradat Khan, called Vazih, <emph>A
                                Translation of the Memoirs of Eradut Khan</emph>, tr. Jonathan
                            Scott, 1786, pp. 92-3.</note></p>
                    <p>“Speculative plunder; contingent spoil; future, long adjourned, uncertain
                        booty; pillage which must enrich a late posterity, and which possibly may
                        not reach posterity at all; these, for any length of time, will never
                        support a mercenary war. The people are in the right. The calculation of
                        profit in all such wars is false. On balancing the account of such wars, ten
                        thousand hogsheads of sugar are purchased at ten thousand times their price.
                        The blood of man should never be shed, but to redeem the blood of man. It is
                        well shed for our family, for our friends, for our God, for our country, for
                        our kind. The rest is vanity; the rest is crime.” Burke, <emph>Regicide
                            Peace, Works</emph>, v. 4, p. 420, 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> Ed.
                                <note><emph>Letters on a Regicide Peace</emph>, n. I, in
                                <emph>Works</emph>, VIII 165. Between 87v and 88r three pages have
                            been torn out.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch15" n="15" type="chapter">
                <head>The Rationale, in French, Principes</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch15scrap99r" n="99r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Guischardt, talking of the manner in which Cesar rectified whatever he found
                        defective in the institutions of his army, remarks that he always went to
                        the rationale, to the first principles of the art, for counsel in repairing
                        the deficiencies which he experienced, “that great man,” says he, “acted
                        always by means of principles.” [F] <emph>Analyse de la campagne de Jules
                            Cesar en Afrique, Memoires Militaires</emph>, t. ii, p. 262.
                            <note>Guischardt, <emph>Mémoires militaires … l’analyse de la campagne
                                de Jules César en Afrique</emph>, c. 12. This is in a very early
                            hand.</note></p>
                    <p>“Lawyers,” says Swift, “of all others seem least to understand the nature of
                        government in general; like underworkmen, who are expert enough at making a
                        single wheel in a clock, but are utterly ignorant how to adjust the several
                        parts, or regulate the movements.” <note><emph>The Sentiments of a Church of
                                England Man, with Respect to Religion and Government</emph>, § 2, in
                                <emph>WorksN</emph>, III 323, <emph>WorksS</emph>, VIII 413. On a
                            pasted in slip in a very early hand (1803?); Swift material on reverse.
                            See <ref target="cpb4ch26">162rv</ref>. On the back of this pasted in
                            slip is a Greek phrase which is to be found again on the top of <ref
                                target="cpb4ch18scrap131v">131v</ref>. One line at the top of the
                            slip has not been identified: <del>Pb. [?] 10. that the preachers ought
                                to find out acceptable words</del>.</note></p>
                    <p>“This art” (of war) says General Lloyd, <emph>Hist. of Late War in
                            Germany</emph>, Pref., p. 6, “like all others, is founded on certain and
                        fixed principles, which are, by their nature, invariable; the application of
                        them only can be varied: but they are in themselves constant.” <note>Lloyd,
                                <emph>Continuation of the History of the Late War in Germany</emph>,
                            v. II, t. II, Preface, pp. vi-vii. In a very early hand
                        (1803?).</note></p>
                    <p>The above quotations are applicable in the teeth of the chateration of the
                        fools why [<emph>sic</emph> who] cry <hi rend="underline">no theorists</hi>!
                        Practical men forever. The following is applicable to the same purpose from
                            <emph>Prospectus d’un Nouveau Dictionnaire de Commerce.</emph> Par M.
                        l’Abbé [André] Morellet.—“One of the most necessary qualities needed to
                        treat with success, the abstract and delicate questions which <hi
                            rend="underline">the theory of commerce</hi> presents, is the <hi
                            rend="underline">removing of all the prepossessions of the state</hi>
                        and of <hi rend="underline">all the prejudices of routine</hi>, and that
                        disposition may more easily be found in a man of letters. What is done is
                        not for him what ought to be done. He raises himself above <hi
                            rend="underline">custom and opinion</hi>; he analyses with more rigour
                        the ideas attached to terms, he separates more easily the equivocal and
                        false meanings of words which often deceive those whom practice has
                        accustomed to the usages of words; he is more rarely the dupe to a sophism
                        than those who have heard it repeated a thousand times before having come to
                        understand them. In a word, free of the cares of state and of custom he is
                        more capable of attaining the truth.” [F] p. 376, Ed., Paris 1769. <note>pp.
                            375-6. From this paragraph on, the hand is 1808 or later.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch15scrap99v" n="99v" type="scrap">
                    <p>Men of practice, the children of prejudice, and of custom. What they have
                        always seen done—what they have always heard repeated—this is the standard
                        of good and evil to them.—Stick to practice—abandon theory—that is—be always
                        savages—never improve—always look backward, never forwards.—Look at the
                        clown—why [<emph>sic</emph> who] so true a disciple of the practical school
                        as he? Ask him to give into any improvement? Whom do you take him for? One
                        who knows no better than that? Newfangled nonsense! (alias theory) Could
                        those who have lived and died, doing as he does (wiser men than modern
                        theorists) have seen all that they saw, and not have found they were in the
                        wrong? You would be for setting up your theory would you?—The practice of
                        our ancestors for us. + Draw this picture bright and strong.</p>
                    <p>Windham boasted of having founded his military reforms on <hi
                            rend="underline">General principles</hi>. Cobbett’s <emph>Parliamentary
                            Debates</emph>, v. 6, pp. 652.—His antagonists <hi rend="underline"
                            >abused</hi> him for following theory, abandoning practice. <note>Debate
                            on Military Establishments of the Country (3/4/1806), Hansard,
                                <emph>PD</emph>, VI 652-3: “Mr. Windham rose and spoke as
                            follows:—Sir; the measures which I am about to propose are little more
                            than the application of those general principles, which I have
                            frequently had occasion to urge to the house, when questions connected
                            with the state of our Military Establishments have made the subject of
                            its deliberations.” See Lord Castlereagh’s speech, <emph>ibid.</emph>,
                            690 and 707. “It cannot but be considered as a serious misfortune for
                            any country to find itself compelled to undertake a fundamental revision
                            of any of its leading establishments. … I trust the house will pointedly
                            discourage any attempt to tamper with our establishments at such a
                            crisis, which require nothing but time and perseverance to render them
                            equal to any purpose we have in view.” See <emph>CPB</emph> I <ref
                                target="cpb1ch4scrap43v">43v</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>“In politics we must treat with principles, and not trouble ourselves about
                        individuals, who fall of themselves into their place as soon as we have
                        given a proper shape to the frame into which they are to enter.” [F] Mad. de
                        Stael, <emph>Rev. Franç.</emph>, i, 400. <note><emph>La révolution
                                françoise; The French Revolution</emph>, I 396, P. II, c.
                        19.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch16" n="16" type="chapter">
                <head>Collections on Ancestry and Birth</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch16scrap117r" n="117r" type="scrap">
                    <p><emph>Birth</emph></p>
                    <p>A Frenchwoman was boasting of her birth, and affirmed that her coat was
                        quartered with the arms of France; which was so far true, that she had the
                        flower de luce [lily] branded on her shoulder. <note>Butler,
                                <emph>Hudibras</emph>, P. I, canto II, fn. to l. 212. Prostitutes
                            were so branded. This whole section seems to be in a pre-1810
                            hand.</note></p>
                    <p>A Spaniard giving himself lofty airs on his family, said the very spelling of
                        his name proved the grandeur of his race: true said another for, looking
                        over the registers of the house of correction the other day, I found that
                        your grandfather had been whipped. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph></note></p>
                    <p>The gentleman thief, who on going to the gallows, insisted on account of his
                        birth for the right hand of the cart. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph></note></p>
                    <p>The cobler, that, when dying, recommended to his son to preserve the honour
                        of the family. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph></note></p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>He (Orsin) was of great descent, and high</l>
                        <l>For splendour and antiquity,</l>
                        <l>And from celestial origin</l>
                        <l>Derived himself in a right line;</l>
                        <l>Not as the ancient heroes did,</l>
                        <l>Who, that their base births might be hid,</l>
                        <l>(Knowing they were of doubtful gender</l>
                        <l>And that they came in at a window)</l>
                        <l>Made Jupiter himself, others</l>
                        <l>O’ th’gods, gallants to their own mothers;</l>
                        <l>Was his undoubted ancestor.</l>
                        <l><emph>Hudibras</emph>, P. I, C. 2, l. 207. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, ll.
                                207-16, 219-20.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                        <l>It was a question whether he</l>
                        <l>Or’s horse were of a family</l>
                        <l>More worshipful: till Antiquaries</l>
                        <l>(After they’d almost por’d out their eyes)</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch16scrap117v" n="117v" type="scrap">
                    <lg>
                        <l>Did very learnedly decide</l>
                        <l>The business on the horse’s side,</l>
                        <l>And proved not only horse, but cows,</l>
                        <l>Nay pigs were of the elder house:</l>
                        <l>For beasts, when man was but a piece</l>
                        <l>Of earth himself, did the earth possess.</l>
                        <l>P. [I], C. 2, l. 465. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, ll. 465-74.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <p>“I maintain that those are most deserving of praise who began from nothing,
                        and yet advanced to greatness by their own efforts, by winning power for
                        themselves and being thought worthy of command.” [G] Luciani, <emph>Dial.
                            Mort.</emph>, 12, Alexander, Hannibal, Minos, and Scipio.
                                <note><emph>The Dialogues of the Dead</emph>, 25(12), in Lucian,
                                <emph>Opera</emph>, I 387-8, Loeb 145.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch17" n="17" type="chapter">
                <head>Wit</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch17scrap119r" n="119r" type="scrap">
                    <p>Quintilian, giving directions to the orator about the use of wit, and
                        describing the spurious kinds, thus says,—“Sarcasm that applies to a number
                        of persons is injudicious. I refer to cases where it is directed against
                        whole nations or classes of society, or against rank and pursuits which are
                        common to many.” [L] <note>Quintilian, <emph>Institutio oratoria</emph>, B.
                            VI, c. 3, § 34, Loeb 457. This and the next two paragraphs are in a very
                            early hand.</note></p>
                    <p>The following, he mentions, was a good retort, [when] a fellow who was
                        himself very ugly said to another, “Even your face was the face of a slave;”
                        to whom the other replied, “Is it your profound conviction that an ugly man
                        must be a slave?” [L] A very good mode of retorting upon a man the charge
                        which though liable to it himself he throws upon others.
                                <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, § 32, Loeb 455.</note></p>
                    <p>An ironical defence of any ill-doing person—He is studying to avoid envy.
                        “Are you trying to placate the envious by abandoning virtue?” [L] Hor.
                            <note>Horace, <emph>Satires</emph>, B. II, n. 3, l. 13, Loeb
                        153.</note></p>
                    <p>“Pleasantry is never good on serious points, because it always regards
                        subjects in that point of view in which it is not the purpose to consider
                        them. It almost always turns on false relations and equivoque, whence jokers
                        by profession usually possess minds as incorrect as they are superficial.”
                        [F] Voltaire, <emph>Dict. Philos.</emph>, Art. Style, p. 232.
                                <note><emph>Dictionnaire Philosophique</emph>, “Style,” § 2, “Sur la
                            corruption du style”; in <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XLIII 232;
                                <emph>Works</emph>, VII-1, pp. 15-16.</note></p>
                    <p>The sailor returning from a long absence said to his wife: “Wife are you
                        turned bawd yet? No, John said she, I am a whore still, and I hope God will
                        keep me so.” <note>North, <emph>The Life of Francis North</emph>, II 328.
                            This and the following item are in a late hand, possibly late
                            1820s.</note></p>
                    <p>People are fond of mockers. [“If for pleasure, and recreation of mind,] every
                        man,” says Hobbes, “is wont to please himself most with those things which
                        stir up laughter, whence he may, according to the nature of that which is
                        ridiculous, by comparison of another man’s defects and infirmities, pass the
                        more current in his own opinion; [and although this be sometimes innocent
                        and without offence, yet it is manifest they are not so much delighted with
                        the society, as their own vain glory].” [L] <emph>De Cive</emph>, c. 1, § 1
                            [<emph>sic</emph>]. <note>In <emph>Opera philosophica</emph>, P. V, p.
                            2; <emph>De Cive or the Citizen</emph>, pp. 22-3, c. 1, § 2.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch18" n="18" type="chapter">
                <head>Literature</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch18scrap131r" n="131r" type="scrap">
                    <p>The useless trifling in which the English scholars pride themselves, spending
                        their lives in learning all the niceties of Greek prosody, is well exposed
                        in a passage of Seneca—<emph>Epist., l.</emph> I, Ep. 49, where he tells us
                        what indignation he felt. “[For this reason I am all the more angry] that
                        some men claim the major portion of this time for superfluous things,—time
                        which, no matter how carefully it is guarded, cannot suffice even for
                        necessary things. Cicero declared that if the number of his days were
                        doubled, he should not have time to read the lyric poets. And you may rate
                        the dialecticians in the same class; but they are foolish in a more
                        melancholy way. The lyric poets are avowedly frivolous; but the
                        dialecticians believe that they are themselves engaged in a serious
                        business. I do not deny that one must cast a glance at dialectic; but it
                        ought to be a mere glance, a sort of greeting from the threshold, merely
                        that one may not be deceived, or judge those pursuits to contain any hidden
                        matters of great worth. Why do you torment yourself and lose weight over
                        some problems which it is more clever to have scorned than to solve? … I
                        have no time to investigate disputed inflections of words, or to try my
                        cunning upon them.” [L] <note>Seneca, <emph>Epistulae morales</emph>, B. I,
                            n. 49, §§ 5-6, Loeb 325-7. Part of the Seneca is used by Montaigne in
                            the essay referred to below.</note></p>
                    <p>The r[h]ythm, the versification, if it is an essential part of poetry, is at
                        least the meanest part. Hear what Montaigne says, liv. I, ch. 25. “I am not
                        one of those who think that rhythm makes a good poem. Let him make a long
                        syllable out of a short if he will, it is no great matter; if the invention
                        is agreeable, if the wit and judgment have well performed their offices, I
                        will say, here is a good poet but a bad versifier.” [F] He tells a curious
                        anecdote to prove how little the Greeks themselves valued the mere
                        versification. “This was Menander’s answer when, as the day drew near for
                        which he had promised a comedy, he was reproved for not having yet set his
                        hand to it: ‘It is composed and ready, it only remains to attach the
                        verses.’ Having,” adds Montaigne, “the circumstances and the substance
                        arranged in his mind, he made small account of the rest.” [F]
                            <emph>Ibid.</emph> Versification—a mere mechanical thing—the task of
                        boys—nobody who chuses to take the trouble can ever fail to make good
                        verses—We see every day that people who have not, (omitting invention,
                        novelty, worth) even an idea, can yet make most harmonious verses. <note>“Of
                            the Education of Children,” in Montaigne, <emph>Essais</emph>, I 344-5,
                            essai 25; <emph>The Essays</emph>, I 150, Essay 26 of B. I.</note></p>
                    <p>“Reader and hearer approve of my works, Aulus, but a certain poet says they
                        are not polished. <hi rend="underline">I don’t care much, for I should
                            prefer the courses of my dinner to please guests rather than
                        cooks</hi>.” [L] Martial, Ad Aulum., <emph>Ep.</emph>, 82, lib. 9.
                            <note>Martial, <emph>Epigrams</emph>, B. IX, n. 81, Loeb 133. The hand
                            of this is about 1808-10 (?).</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch18scrap131v" n="131v" type="scrap">
                    <p>Diploun `wvsin `i mayontew grammata. [Those who learn their letters see twice
                        as much.] <note>Originally on back of Swift item on 99r. The <emph>Thesaurus
                                Linguæ Græcae</emph> could not suggest a classical source for this
                            quotation. Possibly from La Mothe le Vayer, <emph>Œuvres</emph>, Paris
                            1669, VIII 438, “De la lecture des livres et de leur composition,”
                                <emph>Opuscules ou Petits Traitez</emph>, P. III, n. 7. See
                                <emph>CPB</emph> V, <ref target="cpb5ch7">§ VII</ref> for Mill’s use
                            of this author. From this point on, the hand is post 1810.</note></p>
                    <p>“I had earned my pension,” says Burke, (<emph>Lett. to a Noble Lord,
                            Works</emph>, v. 7, p. 396) “before I set my foot in St. Stephen’s
                        Chapel.” He alludes to the knowledge he had laid in, and the preparation he
                        had made for being useful to his country. <note><emph>A Letter to a Noble
                                Lord</emph>, 1796, in <emph>Works</emph>, VII 26.</note></p>
                    <p>“They” (the Indians of Mexico) “express themselves in their own language with
                        great facility. These very Indian chiefs … hold discourses for hours when
                        any great interest excites them to break their natural silence. We observed
                        the same volubility of tongue […] among the Caribs of the lower Orinoco.”
                        [F] Humboldt, <emph>Essai Politique</emph>, p. 99. The volubility of a Pitt,
                        a Fox, a Canning, not therefore so wonderful a thing. <note>Alexander von
                            Humboldt, <emph>Essai politique sur le royaume de
                                Nouvelle-Espagne</emph>, Paris 1811, 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> ed., I
                            99; <emph>Political Essay on the Kingdom of New Spain</emph>, New York
                            1811, I 132, c. VI.</note></p>
                    <p>It is recorded of Robespierre (Pagès, <emph>Hist. Secrète de la revolution
                            Françoise</emph>, t. 2, p. 166) that against no class of men did his
                        rage burn more fiercely than men of letters. <note>François-Xavier Pagès,
                                <emph>Histoire secrète de la révolution françoise</emph>, II 166-7.
                            See <emph>CPB</emph> I <ref target="cpb1ch2scrap85v"
                        >85v</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>[“For let a man look carefully into all that variety of books with which the
                        arts and sciences abound, he will find everywhere endless repetitions of the
                        same thing, varying in the method of treatment, but not new in substance,
                        insomuch that the whole stock, numerous as it appears at first view, proves
                        on examination to be but scanty. And for its value and utility it must be
                        plainly avowed that the wisdom which we have derived principally from the
                        Greeks is like] the boyhood of knowledge, and has the characteristic
                        property of boys: it can talk, but it cannot generate; [for it is fruitful
                        of controversies but barren of works].” [L] Bacon. <note><emph>The Great
                                Instauration</emph>, in <emph>The Philosophical Works</emph>, p.
                            243.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch19" n="19" type="chapter">
                <head>Nobility</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch19scrap139r" n="139r" type="scrap">
                    <p>“The depository of laws cannot be in the hands of the <hi rend="underline"
                            >nobility</hi>. The natural ignorance of the nobility, their indolence
                        and contempt of civil government, require that there should be a body
                        invested with the power of reviving and executing the laws, [which would be
                        otherwise buried in oblivion.”] [F] Montesq., <emph>Esp. des Lois, l.</emph>
                        ii, ch. 4. <note><emph>L’esprit des lois</emph>; in Montesquieu,
                                <emph>Œuvres</emph>, II 249; <emph>The Spirit of the Laws</emph>, p.
                            17, translation modified in the first sentence to fit Mill’s
                            strengthening of Montesquieu’s point. This is in a very early
                            hand.</note></p>
                    <p>“All for ourselves, and nothing for other people, seems, in all ages of the
                        world to have been the vile maxim of the masters of mankind.” <emph>Wealth
                            of Nations</emph>, v. ii, p. 125. <note>Smith, <emph>The Wealth of
                                Nations</emph>, B. III, c. 4, ¶ 10. In an early hand.</note></p>
                    <p>Burke, who uses all sorts of arguments, as the ever varying nature of his
                        occasions presents the demand for them, can talk with emphasis of the
                        natural, and necessary <hi rend="underline">idleness, ignorance</hi> and
                        mental imbecility of the Great. The Duke of Bedford, the Duke who attacked
                        his pension in 1796, was reckoned one of the very finest specimens—a model
                        of an English nobleman:—“I challenge,” says Burke, (<emph>Lett. to a Noble
                            lord, Works</emph>, v. 7, p. 379) “the Duke of Bedford as a juror to
                        pass upon the value of my services. Whatever his natural parts may be, I
                        cannot recognize in his few and <hi rend="underline">idle</hi> years the
                        competence to judge of my long and laborious life. If I can help it he shall
                        not be on the inquest of my <emph>quantum meruit.</emph> Poor rich man! <hi
                            rend="underline">He can hardly know any thing of public industry in its
                            exertions, or can estimate its compensations when its work is done</hi>.
                        I have no doubt of his Grace’s readiness in all the calculations of vulgar
                        arithmetic; but I shrewdly suspect that he is little studied in the theory
                        of moral proportions; and has never learned the rule of three in the
                        arithmetic of policy and state. …</p>
                    <p>“I was not, like the Duke of Bedford, swaddled and rocked, and dandled into a
                        legislator. <emph>Nitor in adversum</emph> is the motto for a man like me. I
                        possessed not one of the qualities, nor cultivated one of the arts, that
                        recommend men to the favour and protection of the great. I was not made for
                        a minion or a tool. … I had no arts but manly arts.” <note><emph>A Letter to
                                a Noble Lord</emph>, 1796, in <emph>Works</emph>, VIII 9-10, 27-8.
                            In an early hand.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch19scrap139v" n="139v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“He is but a poor observer, who has not seen, that the generality of peers,
                        far from supporting themselves in a state of independent greatness, are but
                        too apt to fall into an oblivion of their proper dignity, and to run
                        headlong into an abject servitude.” Burke, <emph>Thoughts on the cause of
                            the Present Discontents</emph>, p. 28. See Gibbon’s poor dissertation on
                        the descent of ancestorial virtue, at the beginning of his
                            <emph>Life.</emph>
                        <note><emph>Thoughts on the Cause of the Present Discontents</emph>, in
                            Burke, <emph>Works</emph>, II 246; <emph>Memoirs of my Life and
                                Writings</emph>, in Gibbon, <emph>The Miscellaneous Works</emph>, I
                            1-4. In a post-1810 hand.</note>
                        <note>Sentence on Gibbon added later.</note></p>
                    <p>An order of nobles incompatible with good government—<emph>Vindiciæ
                            Gallicae</emph>, p. 67, etc. <note>Mackintosh, <emph>Vindiciæ
                                gallicae</emph>, pp. 67-76. “The Nobility, the Priesthood, the
                            Judicial Aristocracy, were unfit to be members of a free government,
                            because their <emph>corporate</emph> character had been formed under
                            arbitrary establishments. … To the plenitude of the Royal power were
                            attached those immense and magnificent privileges, which divided France
                            into distinct nations; which exhibited a Nobility monopolizing the
                            rewards the offices of the State, and a people degraded to political
                                <emph>helotism.</emph>” (pp. 70, 73-4.)</note></p>
                    <p>In an enlightened country a man of education is in no want of motives to
                        elevation of conduct, to alienation from meanness (whatever is meant by
                        meanness) far better than the pride of artificial preferences, inspiring
                        contempt for mankind, and contempt for virtue, brutal self-conceit. Ancient
                        rank is merely the relict of ancient domination, the power of oppressing
                        mankind. “The celebrated saying of the regent, duke of Orleans, [is
                        sufficient to destroy the foundation of the <emph>Spirit of the
                        Laws</emph>]: ‘This is a perfect courtier—he has neither spirit nor
                        honour.’” [F] Voltaire, <emph>Diction. Phil.</emph>, Mot Honneur.
                                <note><emph>Dictionnaire Philosophique</emph>, in
                                <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XLI 104; <emph>Works</emph>, VI-2, p. 101. See
                                <emph>CPB</emph> I, <ref target="cpb1ch4scrap58v"
                        >58v</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>See Bacon’s Essay on Nobility, where all the political effects are condemned
                        as evil. <note><emph>Essays</emph>, n. 14, “Of Nobility,” in <emph>The
                                Philosophical Works</emph>, pp. 750-1. A typical comment: “But for
                            democracies, they need it not; and they are commonly more quiet and less
                            subject to sedition, than where there are stirps of nobles. … A numerous
                            nobility causeth poverty and inconvenience in a state, for it is a
                            surcharge of expense.”</note></p>
                    <p>“The great never look upon their inferiors as their fellow creatures.” Smith,
                            <emph>Mor. Sent.</emph>, v. I, p. 136.—To the same purpose Shaftesbury,
                        commenting on <emph>rarus enim ferme sensus communis in illa Fortuna</emph>,
                        [For in those high places regard for others is seldom to be found] in the
                        Essay on the freedom of Wit and Humour. <note>Smith, <emph>The Theory of
                                Moral Sentiments</emph>, P. I, § 3, c. 2, “Of the origin of
                            ambition, and the distinction of ranks” Shaftesbury,
                                <emph>Characteristicks</emph>, I 103ff., “An Essay on the Wit and
                            Humour,” P. III, § 1: “But for <emph>Humanity</emph> or <emph>Sense of
                                Publick Good</emph>, and the <emph>common Interest</emph> of
                            Mankind, ’twas no such deep Satir to question this was properly
                                <emph>the Spirit of a Court.</emph> ’Twas difficult to apprehend
                            what <emph>Community</emph> subsisted among Courtiers; or what
                                <emph>Publick</emph> between an absolute Prince and his
                            Slave-Subjects.” Latin quotation from Juvenal, <emph>Satires</emph>,
                            VIII, l. 73, Loeb 163.</note></p>
                    <p>“For what is meant by ennobling, except declaring that the <emph>Tiers
                            Etat</emph>, in other words the nation, is made up of plebeians; that it
                        is not honourable to be merely a citizen, and that certain meritorious
                        individuals have acquired a title to be raised above this state of
                        humility?” [F] Mad. de Stael, <emph>Rev. Franç.</emph>, iii, 79.
                                <note><emph>La révolution françoise; The French Revolution</emph>,
                            III 75, P. V, c. 8.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch20" n="20" type="chapter">
                <head>On National Matters</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch20scrap144r" n="144r" type="scrap">
                    <p>In the conduct of the national business the vulgar think that what our own
                        ministers transact with foreign ministers ought to be praised, that we may
                        not seem to put our own country in the wrong. But the enlightened love of
                        our country seems to prompt the following sentiment; to render us the more
                        indignant and inexorable against those ministers who have mismanaged the
                        national affairs, when they might have wrought to the nation the happiest
                        effects. It seems not to dictate adulation, exculpation, the varnishing
                        over, the putting a fair gloss on, etc., of the mismanagement, but regret,
                        offence, and reprobation. <note>These three pages are in an early hand
                                (<emph>c.</emph> 1806-7; see date of ¶ 3 below).</note></p>
                    <p>You hear it said that public executions deter men from crimes. Rather, it
                        should be said, that the boldness, and resolution with which convicts now
                        meet death, teach the most effectual lesson of fearlessness and hardihood in
                        crime. Such examples are not calculated to render criminals afraid of death,
                        but to make them despise it. It thus becomes a part of their trade to learn
                        to despise [death]. It is far from a good to render bad men not afraid of
                        death. You have then lost hold of your most powerful chain to them, and
                        render them more daring, and adventurous in their enormities.</p>
                    <p>The Capon, one of the most determined flatterers of Majesty among lords, was
                        pleased in the august assembly to which he belongs, in the debate on the
                        negotiation on friday 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Jan. 1807, to stretch his
                        conscientious voice in defence of Hanover. He told us, that if our honour
                        commanded us to stand by our other allies, by the Emperor of Russia, by the
                        King of Naples, it commanded us to stand by the Elector of Hanover; and not
                        give up his dominions. Why did we not then demand to negotiate in common
                        with him? Why was he not associated in the negotiation? But was he really
                        our ally, when you tell us his territories were unjustly attacked because
                        they were not at war. He was then our ally without joining in our quarrel! a
                        new species of alliance. Were all our allies of this sort we should be much
                        the better for them! And we should certainly deserve their gratitude, if,
                        when they did so little for us, we stand up as stoutly for all their
                        interests.—Dishonourable, you say to desert our ally? What then was it in
                        that ally never to join us? But if we have an ally, of this description, is
                        it not lawful for us to say, it is an unprofitable alliance and we wish to
                        get rid of it? But why should not that ally make sacrifices at least equal
                        to others? We were willing to let our ally of Naples be shorn of all his
                        dominions, but a certain outport. If this was honourable, as much would have
                        been so to our ally of Hanover. <note>Speech of Lord Grenville (the
                            Paymaster-General) in the debate on Negotiations with France (2/1/1807),
                            Hansard, <emph>PD</emph>, VIII 261-4.</note></p>
                    <p>We are told that it would be dishonourable not to protect our sovereign’s
                        property. What is meant by our sovereign’s property? Are we to suppose that
                        he has any property dearer than the lives and property of his British
                        subjects? Does he wish that these should be shed and expended for any thing
                        but the good of the nation? What terrible ideas, those thoughtless men would
                        excite of their sovereign? Can any interest be supposed so precious to him
                        as the welfare of that British people, who upon him and his family have so
                        largely bestowed [their affection]? Does that not injure most deeply the
                        interests of the sovereign which most touches the lives and property of his
                        people? Ought he not to be ready to sacrifice himself, and every thing which
                        belongs to him in defence of those lives and that property?</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch20scrap144v" n="144v" type="scrap">
                    <p>We are told he has a people those whom it is his duty to care for. If any man
                        has incompatible duties, let him renounce the situation which creates them.
                        No man can serve two masters. If the sovereign is the servant of his people,
                        the rule you see literally holds. It is impossible for a man to be the king
                        of two peoples whose interests are different and often contrary. He must
                        hurt by turns the interests of both. The interest of the one people may
                        require him to [do] directly the contrary of what he is prevailed upon to do
                        for the interests of the other. How often has this been exemplified in the
                        case of which we are speaking. In a negotiation with France, it would be for
                        the interest of this country to give up Hanover for some good equivalent:
                        And how much would it have lately been for the interest of the poor
                        Hanoverians to be able to court the friendship of Bonaparte? To what
                        dreadful calamities, incessantly repeated, are they not exposed by belonging
                        to the King of Great Britain? Of what woes is that single circumstance the
                        cause to them, woes against which they can receive no protection, and of
                        which they can see no end! Let us hear no more of the affection towards them
                        of their elector. He is the entire cause of their wretchedness. He holds a
                        station which compels them to suffer misery; and he ought either to renounce
                        that station, or to let them chuse an elector, whose situation is less
                        incompatible with their happiness. How mean spirited in that elector to seek
                        to rule over a people whom he cannot protect, and whom he exposes to every
                        calamity? Is this the affection to his people which we are called upon to
                        admire?</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch21" n="21" type="chapter">
                <head>Artifices</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch21scrap147r" n="147r" type="scrap">
                    <p>It is a standing artifice—where any base principle is <del>resolutely</del>
                        adopted, and the resolution is fairly formed of acting upon it, without the
                        power of concealing the motive, boldly to avow and justify it—and not only
                        to justify, but to lay it down as an obligatory line of conduct, to claim
                        for it the merit of a duty—Thus corruption, is represented as a beneficial
                        principle in the British constitution—Thus wordiness is defended as a virtue
                        in law writings—Thus the glorious uncertainty of the law—Its delays,
                        vexation, and expense,—the price paid for British liberty—The trampling down
                        of a people by a tyrannical aristocracy, the principle of social order—
                            <note>Original title of this section: ‘War’; see <ref
                                target="cpb4ch14scrap87r">87r</ref> for the deleted Voltaire item.
                            The remaining items on 147r are in an early (1803-08?) hand.</note></p>
                    <p>Those who are accused of any real malversation constantly try to throw
                        accusations, either real or imaginary upon those who assail them. Those who
                        are accused of pillaging the people in this country, and of defending the
                        institutions under cover of which they are pillaged, call their accusers
                        Jacobins, Frenchmen, anarchists, enemies of the government, enemies of
                        order. The perturbizers in the French revolution were masters in the same
                        art. M. Bailly says (<emph>Memoires</emph>, t. iii, p. 227) “A constant
                        manoeuvre, since the revolution has been for men under suspicion to make
                        suspect those who are watching them.” [F] <note><emph>Mémoires d’un témoin
                                de la révolution</emph>, III 226-7. Between 155v and 156r one page
                            has been torn out.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch22" n="22" type="chapter">
                <head>Liberty</head>
                <p><note>Original title of this section <hi rend="bold"><del>Medical
                            Facts</del></hi>. Deleted material follows.</note>
                    <del>Capivaccius, it is said, saved the only heir of a noble family by ordering
                        him to lie between two nurses in the flower of their age, and suck their
                        breasts.</del>
                    <note>H. Capivaccius, Practica medicana[?], Frankfort, 1794,
                    unverified.</note></p>
                <p><del>Forestus tells us, that a youth at Bologna, of twenty nine years of age,
                        labouring under a true marasmus, lived upon the milk of a beautiful young
                        nurse of eighteen years of age, who lay in the same bed with him, by which
                        means his emaciated body was well restored.</del>
                    <note>P. Forestus Observationum et curationum chirurgicarum[?], Frankfort, 1634,
                        unverified.</note>
                    <note>These two references may have come from Mill’s attendance at medical
                        lectures in Edinburgh in the late 1790s, in fact, these two quotations add
                        support to the supposition of J.S. Mill that he may have studied medicine;
                        see Bain, p. 17. This material is in an exceptionally early hand, a large,
                        flowery, copper-plate, very much like that at the end of this volume; see
                            <ref target="cpb4ch25scrap173v">173v</ref>.</note></p>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap160r" n="160r" type="scrap">
                    <p>How absurd is the attempt to make odious Sidney, and palliate Charles the
                        Second for his murder, by saying, as Hume, or even as Burnett does, that his
                        head was incurably filled with notions about a republic! Of his celebrated
                            <emph>Discourse on government</emph> the very title of one of the
                        sections is, ch. ii, Sect. xvi, <emph>The best governments of the world have
                            been composed, of Monarchy, Democracy, and Aristocracy.</emph> This
                        proposition he goes on to prove by a long induction of particulars; and
                        among other things expressly says, “As for democracy he” (Filmer) “may say
                        what he pleases of it; and I believe it can suit only with the convenience
                        of a small town, accompanied with such circumstances as are seldom found.
                        But this no way obliges men to run into the other extreme, inasmuch as the
                        variety of forms between mere democracy and absolute monarchy is almost
                        infinite. And if I should undertake to say there never was a good government
                        in the world, that did not consist of the three simple species, monarchy,
                        aristocracy, and democracy, I think I might make it good.” <note>Algernon
                            Sydney, <emph>Discourses Concerning Government</emph>, 1763, p. 130;
                            Hume, <emph>The History of England</emph>, VIII 196-8, c. 69; Gilbert
                            Burnet, <emph>History of His Own Time</emph>, 1753, II 406-11, B. III.
                            Mill somewhat distorts both criticisms. Hume remarks that what makes the
                            the court and ministry “blameable was the illegal method, which they
                            took for effecting their purpose against them.” This and the next four
                            paragraphs are in an early (pre-1808?) hand.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap160v" n="160v" type="scrap">
                    <p>It is remarkable that Athens was so far from being a pure democracy that both
                        Sir Robert Filmer, and Algernon Sidney represent it as a species of
                        monarchy, in the functions of the Archon. See Algernon Sidney’s
                            <emph>Discourses on Government</emph>, [p. 130,] ch. ii, Sect. 16.
                            <note>Above this paragraph the first line of the Voltaire item four
                            paragraphs below has been deleted.</note></p>
                    <p>The same author enumerates the Lacedemonian government, that of the Dorian
                        states, the Athenian, and other Ionian states, Rome under the consuls,
                        Venice, Genoa, Lucca [<emph>sic</emph> Luca], Germany, and the other Gothic
                        governments, as instances of mixed governments, including monarchy,
                        aristocracy and democracy. <emph>Ibid.</emph>
                        <note>pp. 130-1.</note></p>
                    <p>A good title of a section—“Man’s natural love to liberty is tempered by
                        reason, which originally is his nature.” <emph>Ibid.</emph>, Sect. XX.
                            <note>p. 151.</note></p>
                    <p>A very good and sensible note in Voltaire’s <emph>Louis XIV</emph>, on the
                        subject of the pensions which that monarch gave to Charles II and other
                        Englishmen, says, “Dalrymple had the list of the pensioners of the King of
                        France printed, with the sums given to each. One found on it the name of
                        Algernon Sidney with a sum which would not have sufficed to attract his
                        secretary. It is probable that Braillon deceived Louis XIV with these lists
                        as other men have deceived him since with lists of conversions, or (what is
                        still more probable) that some intriguing underling deceived Braillon, and
                        kept for himself the money which he pretended to have accepted for Sidney.”
                        [F] v. I, p. 346 in ch. 10. <note><emph>Le siècle de Louis XIV</emph>, c.
                            10, fn. 14, in <emph>Œuvres</emph>, XX 326.</note></p>
                    <p>Demosthenes tells an admirable story of Iphicrates [?Philocrates?]. He was
                        negotiating with the Lacedaemonians, who asked him what ground of trust in
                        them he would wish to receive. In his opinion, he said, there was only one;
                        if they would shew, that if they should desire to do harm, they would not
                        have the power; for that they would desire, he well knew. So long then as
                        they should have the power, there could be no ground of trust. <emph>Orat.
                            Adv. Aristocratem</emph>, p. 445. This is a speech which still more
                        remarkably suits a people towards their rulers; and is a maxim that should
                        never be lost out of sight. <note>Demosthenes, <emph>Against
                                Aristocrates</emph>, 116-17(659), Loeb 295. Nepos has Iphicrates as
                            the negotiator and Bacon follows him, but Demosthenes quite clearly
                            gives Philocrates. See <emph>De sapientia veterum</emph>, n. 5, “Styx:
                            or Treaties,” in Bacon, <emph>The Philosophical Works</emph>, p. 828,
                            for his version of the moral.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap161r" n="161r" type="scrap">
                    <p>A fine passage against kings in Cowper’s <emph>Task</emph>, Book 5<hi
                            rend="sup">th</hi>, near the beginning. <note><emph>The Task</emph>, B.
                            V, ll. 179-379, in <emph>Works</emph>, II 165; see also
                        167-9.</note></p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>… Nations would do well</l>
                        <l>T’extort their truncheons from the puny hands</l>
                        <l>Of heroes, whose infirm and baby minds</l>
                        <l>Are gratified with mischief, and who spoil</l>
                        <l>Because men suffer it, their toy the world. <note><hi rend="bold"
                                    >N.B.</hi> Mill did not include this passage, it has been
                                provided by Fenn for illustration.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <p>Another in a short poem of Swift, entitled <emph>Rhapsody</emph> (I think, on
                        poetry). <note><emph>On Poetry, A Rhapsody</emph>, 1733, ll. 205-16, in
                                <emph>WorksN</emph>, XI 292, <emph>WorksS</emph>, XIV
                        310.</note></p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>A prince, the moment he is crown’d,</l>
                        <l>Inherits every virtue round,</l>
                        <l>As emblems of the sovereign power,</l>
                        <l>Like other baubles in the Tower;</l>
                        <l>Is generous, valiant, just, and wise,</l>
                        <l>And so continues till he dies:</l>
                        <l>His Humble senate this professes,</l>
                        <l>In all their speeches, votes, addresses.</l>
                        <l>But once you fix him in a tomb,</l>
                        <l>His virtues fade, his vices bloom;</l>
                        <l>And each perfection, wrong imputed,</l>
                        <l>Is fully at his death confuted. <note><hi rend="bold">N.B.</hi> Mill did
                                not include this passage, it has been provided by Fenn for
                                illustration.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <p>There is an expression in Montesquieu, which well depicts the state of human
                        nature under despotism. <emph>La il n’y a que des miserables qui pillent, et
                            des miserables qui sont pillés.</emph> [There are none there but
                        wretches, some pillaging and others pillaged.] (<emph>Esp. des Lois,
                            l.</emph> XVI, ch. 10.) How far is this different from our state under
                        the British government? <note><emph>L’esprit des lois</emph>, in
                                <emph>Œuvres</emph>, II 516; <emph>The Spirit of the Laws</emph>, p.
                            257. See Mill’s use of this expression in his article “The State of the
                            Nation,” <emph>London Review</emph>, I (April 1835), 6.</note></p>
                    <p>There is a curious observation by the Jesuit Acosta (<emph>Natural and Moral
                            History of the Indies</emph>, B. VI, ch. 2) wherein he describes
                        despotism as the mark of barbarism. “It is apparent,” says he, “that the
                        manner wherein these barbarous people shew their barbarism, was in their
                        government and manner of command: for the more that men approach to reason,
                        the more mild is their government and less insolent; the kings and lords are
                        more tractable, agreeing better with their subjects, acknowledging them
                        equal in nature, though inferior in duty and care of the commonwealth. But
                        amongst the Barbarians all is contrary, for that their government is
                        tyrannous, using their subjects like beasts, and seeking to be reverenced
                        like gods.” <note>Joseph de Acosta, <emph>The Naturall and Morall Historie
                                of the East and West Indies</emph>, 1604, p. 453, B. VI, c.
                            11.</note></p>
                    <p>In many countries an appearance of liberty may be established—some thing that
                        the authors of the abuses may trumpet forth as liberty, <del>without</del>
                        where the happiness of the people is any thing rather than improved. “A
                        regular and constant system of oppression has succeeded to the tumults and
                        storms of conquest; and we behold, with a degree of indifference, the
                        various ranks of slaves assassinating each other with their chains, for the
                        amusement of their masters.” [F] The French expression from Raynal,
                            <emph>Hist. Phil. des deux Indes</emph>, Liv. VI, § 1.
                                <note><emph>Histoire philosophique et politique des établissemens et
                                du commerce des Européens dans les deux Indes</emph>, III 204;
                                <emph>A Philosophical and Political History of the Settlements and
                                Trade of the Europeans in the East and West Indies</emph>, B. VI, p.
                            1.</note></p>
                    <p>Among men of wealth, and hereditary distinctions there is a natural love of
                        arbitrary power. In the natural competition of talents they are conscious
                        that they would sink low. Their habitual love of ease makes them look upon
                        the dead calm of a despotism as a state of enjoyment, the active energy of a
                        republic as a state of misery.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap161v" n="161v" type="scrap">
                    <p>The period of disaster is unhappily a period when it is most natural for the
                        oppressed to obtain from the oppressor an alleviation of his burthens. This
                        observation is extorted on a very memorable occasion, from one of the most
                        determined admirers that ever was, of hands graced by the grasp of power,
                        Mr. Mitford. “With the various miseries which a war of 27 years diffused
                        among those called citizens of the Greek nation, it brought a very general
                        alleviation of evil to that more numerous portion of mankind, the Grecian
                        slaves. When all neighbouring republics were friendly the slave looked
                        around in vain for refuge from the cruelty of an inhuman master; <hi
                            rend="underline">but if they were hostile, it behoved equally the
                            wealthy despot of many slaves, and the poor tyrant of one, to beware how
                            he set the wretch upon comparing the risk of desertion with the hope of
                            a better service</hi>.” Mitford’s <emph>Greece</emph>, ch. XXI, Sect. 1.
                                <note><emph>The History of Greece</emph>, V 9.</note></p>
                    <p>“That excellent principle of the English constitution, the only one on which
                        a free government can be firmly founded, that the aggregate of private good
                        should make public good, and its corollary, that the rights of individuals
                        once established by law, should be ever held sacred, seems to have been a
                        principle of Theseus’s kingdom and Solon’s republic.” Mitford’s
                            <emph>Greece</emph>, ch. XXI, Sect. 2. <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>,
                            41.</note></p>
                    <p>[“The great defect of the constitutions of Theseus and Solon, was the want of
                        … the principle of representation. The advantage of this is … ] [t]hat
                        responsibility may be attached to every constituted power; by which alone,
                        whatever the names or forms of the government may be, real despotism can be
                        obviated.” <emph>Id., Ibid.</emph>
                        <note><emph>Ibid.</emph>, 42.</note></p>
                    <p>The progress of luxury—that soft and effeminate indulgence and love of ease,
                        which becomes the characteristic of the wealthy, disposes them against
                        freedom—makes them look to the protection of arbitrary power to preserve
                        them in their inactivity—and apprehend, as the greatest of evils the
                        necessity of competition with the active body of the people.</p>
                    <p>“Whoever,” says Dean Swift—<emph>Sentiments of a Church of England
                        man</emph>—“argues in defence of absolute power in a single person—though he
                        offers the old plausible plea that it is his opinion which he cannot help
                        unless he be convinced—ought in all free states to be treated as the common
                        enemy of mankind.” <note>§ 2, in <emph>WorksN</emph>, III 314,
                                <emph>WorksS</emph>, VIII 403. This and the next item on a pasted-in
                            scrap, on paper similar to that of the notebook itself.</note></p>
                    <p>“Arbitrary power” […] <emph>Id., Ib.</emph>, “I look upon as a greater evil
                        than anarchy itself, as much as a savage is [in] a happier state of life
                        than a slave at the oar.” <note><emph>WorksN</emph>, 313,
                                <emph>WorksS</emph>, 402.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap162r" n="162r" type="scrap">
                    <p>If you ask, says Lord Littleton, “how it is possible to bribe a whole nation
                        to the undoing of itself? It is not possible, I answer. <hi rend="underline"
                            >But the misfortune of our government is, that the majority of the
                            representative body is chosen not by the whole nation, but by a
                                <emph>small</emph> and <emph>very</emph> mean part of it</hi>.”
                            <emph>Pers. Lett.</emph>, 54 [<emph>sic</emph>]. <note><emph>Letters
                                from a Persian in England to His Friend at Ispahan</emph>, letter
                            53, in Lyttelton, <emph>Miscellaneous Works</emph>, I 302. This pasted
                            in item, as well as the one below, is clearly cut from the same sheet of
                            notes as that pasted in at <ref target="cpb4ch15scrap99r">99r</ref>. On
                            the reverse side is a deleted Swift item which continues the quotation
                            on the reverse of the item at <ref target="cpb4ch15scrap99r">99r</ref>.
                            Like similar material at II <ref target="cpb2ch1scrap8r">8r</ref>, and V
                                <ref target="cpb5ch20scrap102r">102r</ref> it is in an early hand
                            (pre-1808). The item at V <ref target="cpb5ch20scrap102r">102r</ref> has
                            an 1802 watermark. The material on the reverse of these pasted-in slips
                            may be found in the addenda to this volume, § <ref target="cpb4ch26"
                                >XVI</ref>. The Burke item, two paragraphs below, is also pasted in,
                            and in the same hand and on the same paper.</note></p>
                    <p>I ordered, says Gulliver, “that <hi rend="underline">the senate</hi> of Rome
                        might appear before me in one large chamber, and <hi rend="underline">a
                            modern representative</hi> in counterview in another. <hi
                            rend="underline">The first seemed to be an assembly of heroes and
                            demi-gods; the other a knot of pedlars, pick-pockets, highway-men and
                            bullies</hi>.” <note><emph>Gulliver’s Travels</emph>, P. III, c. 7, in
                            Swift, <emph>WorksN</emph>, IX 217, <emph>WorksS</emph>, XII
                        252.</note></p>
                    <p>“In truth,” says Mr. Burke, “the tribe of vulgar politicians,” (by which he
                        does not mean ignorant political reasoners, but the mechanical, selfish
                        instruments of politics, “the creatures of the desks,” as he calls them,
                        “and the creatures of favour”) “are the lowest of our species.”
                                <note><emph>Letters on a Regicide Peace</emph>, n. II, in
                                <emph>Works</emph>, VIII 218.</note></p>
                    <p>In those days of Charles II when, as <del>almost</del> all men now
                        acknowledge, this country groaned under a base and illiberal despotism,
                            <del>there were not</del> it was the favourite theme, to talk of the
                        excellencies of the constitution, as a perfect system of freedom, as the
                        precious middle, standing at the due and delightful distance from all
                        extremes, as incapable, without all the dangers of anarchy, of receiving a
                        particle more of liberty, as proving by its essential properties all those
                        members of the nation to be perturbators and traitors who expressed so much
                        as a desire that any thing were otherwise than it was.—See a most
                        instructive passage to this effect, and a most instructive note by Mr.
                        Malone, Dryden’s <emph>Prose Works</emph>, v. ii, pp. 6, 7, etc. See, too,
                        the passage in Fox’s <emph>Work</emph>, where he talks of our government
                        having then attained theoretic perfection—and this being a proof that all
                        security for good government depends on the men who administer it.
                            <note>Dryden, <emph>Prose Works</emph>, ed. E. Malone, II 6-7 and 6fn.
                            Dryden remarks in his preface to <emph>All for Love</emph> that the
                            English government was “so equal and so well poised … a government which
                            has all the advantages of liberty beyond a commonwealth, and all the
                            marks of kingly sovereignty without the danger of a tyranny. Both my
                            nature, as I am an Englishman, and my reason, as I am a man, have bred
                            in me a loathing to that specious name of a Republic; that
                            mock-appearance of a liberty, where all who have not part in the
                            government are slaves; and slaves they are of a viler note than such as
                            are subjects to an absolute dominion. … The nature of our government,
                            above all others, is exactly suited both to the situation of our country
                            and the temper of our natives; … neither the arbitrary power of one in a
                            monarchy, nor of many in a commonwealth, could make us greater than we
                            are.” Malone adds in a footnote that “I am however too well apprized of
                            the rooted enmity borne by the ‘<emph>incorrigible</emph> Jacobins’ of
                            the present day to the glorious inheritance which we have received from
                            our ancestors, and of their unceasing endeavours to destroy the noblest
                            fabrick which human wisdom ever devised.” See also C.J. Fox, <emph>A
                                History of the Early Part of the Reign of James the Second</emph>,
                            1808, pp. 21-2, c. I: “[In 1679] our constitution had arrived at its
                            greatest theoretical perfection. … Here we are then at the best moment
                            of the best constitution that ever human wisdom framed. What follows? A
                            time of oppression and misery, not arising from external or accidental
                            causes, such as war, pestilence, or famine, nor even from any such
                            alteration of the laws as might be supposed to impair this boasted
                            perfection, but from a corrupt and wicked administration, which all the
                            so much admired checks of the constitution were not able to prevent. How
                            vain then, how idle, how presumptuous, is the opinion, that laws can do
                            every thing! and how weak and pernicious the maxim founded upon it, that
                            measures, not men, are to be attended to.” Mill quoted from this passage
                                <emph>in extenso</emph> in his review, “Fox’s History of the Reign
                            of James II,” <emph>Annual Review and History of Literature</emph>, VII
                            (1808), 104-5.</note>
                        <note>Last sentence added later.</note></p>
                    <p>The burthens of the Social Union are in this country shared most unequally
                        between the rich, and the inferior ranks including the middle and the
                        lowest. The scale of taxation so formed as to favour extremely the rich.
                        This in respect to pecuniary burthens.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap162v" n="162v" type="scrap">
                    <p>In respect to services, the case is more glaring at least—the inequality, and
                        oppression more indisputable. The Services of the higher orders are all paid
                        for—all so highly paid for that there is never any want of volunteers for
                        the <del>service places</del> duties. The services of the lower orders are
                        demanded without adequate payment and the assistance of force is taken to
                        supply the deficiency—Witness, the pressing of seamen—the pressing of
                        soldiers, as by the ballot—of common jurymen—for the corvées.—It is highly
                        worthy of observation, that it is the invariable, infallibly
                            [<emph>sic</emph> infallible] tendency of civilization, in its fair
                        progress to lessen that inequality. It is natural in a rude and barbarous
                        period, for those into whose hands power has fallen, to seat themselves by
                        means of it on the necks of those who have it not, and who are too feeble
                        and ignorant to resist. Civilization makes perpetual alterations as it
                        ceasingly advances, in this bad state.—NB Illustrate this.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps the word <hi rend="underline">liberty</hi> should not be too lavishly
                        used. Many persons have prejudices against it. They think it synonimous with
                        democracy, and that with anarchy. <hi rend="underline">Good government</hi>
                        a better word—with this not so many unfavourable associations. The prejudice
                        against such words make sad havoc with such men as Mitford, who takes a
                        liking to a man the moment he hears of any one who is accused of being a
                        pursuer of arbitrary power, and never can believe any good of the man who is
                        accused of being in love with liberty. Dionysius he washes what
                            [<emph>sic</emph> white] as milk; by a species of historical
                        disquisition, by which Cromwell, or Bonaparte might be idolized. Whatever is
                        handed down to us concerning Dionysius, we are told by men who were fond of
                        Democracy—therefore not one word they have said against him is to be
                        believed. But they represent him as a man of mixed qualities—many very good
                        ones. Take all the good qualities—</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap163r" n="163r" type="scrap">
                    <p>make them up into a character by themselves—insist that as we have these
                        qualities only from his enemies, we may add a great deal to the good they
                        tell us—the character thus made up is a good one—then draw the sweeping
                        conclusion that with this good character it is inconsistent to be guilty of
                        any evil—and so upon this ground deny sturdily all the evil that is laid to
                        his charge.—Whatever the republican writers like, Mr. Mitford must dislike,
                        and whatever they dislike, Mr. Mitford must like. Dionysius they represent
                        as a tyrant, Mr. Mitford says he was an admirable citizen—Timoleon they say
                        was a champion of freedom—Mr. Mitford makes him out a tyrant.
                            <note>Dionysius the Elder, of Corinth, is discussed in Mitford’s
                                <emph>History of Greece</emph>, VII cc. 30-1; see esp. c. 31, § 1,
                            p. 113. For Timoleon, see <emph>ibid.</emph>, c. 33, § 3, pp. 251-4. Cf.
                            Aristotle’s view of Dionysius above at <emph>CPB</emph> I <ref
                                target="cpb1ch4scrap51r">51r</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>“Liberty must be limited in order to be possessed. The degree of restraint it
                        is impossible in any case to settle precisely. But it ought to be the
                        constant aim of every wise public counsel, to find out by cautious
                        experiments, and rational, cool endeavours, with how little, not how much of
                        this restraint, the community can subsist. For liberty is a good to be
                        improved, and not an evil to be lessened. It is not only a private blessing
                        of the first order, but the vital spring and energy of the state itself,
                        which has just so much life and vigour as there is liberty in it. But
                        whether liberty be advantageous or not, (for I know it is a fashion to deny
                        the very principle) none will dispute, etc.” Burke, <emph>Letter to the
                            Sheriffs of Bristol—Works</emph>, v. ii, p. 140—Edit. 4<hi rend="sup"
                            >to</hi>. <note>In <emph>Works</emph>, III 185-6.</note></p>
                    <p>Hume says, it is “agreeable to the spirit of a free government, that no less
                        indignation should be excited by the view of a violated constitution, than
                        by the ravages of the most enormous tyranny.” <emph>Hist. Eng.</emph>, v. 6,
                        p. 375. <note><emph>The History of England</emph>, c. 54.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch22scrap163v" n="163v" type="scrap">
                    <p>The excellence of “our legal constitution,” says Blackstone,
                            <emph>Comment.</emph>, v. 3, p. 422, “is the genuine offspring of that
                        spirit of equal liberty which is the singular felicity of Englishmen.” NB
                        Among the other fruits of liberty is that of having good laws.
                                <note><emph>Commentaries</emph>, III 423, B. III, c. 26.</note></p>
                    <p>Dr. Johnson said—“Charles the Second was licentious in this practice, but he
                        always had a reverence for what was good. Charles the Second knew his people
                        and rewarded merit. The Church was at no time better filled than in his
                        reign. He was the best king we ever had from his time till the reign of his
                        present Majesty, except James the Second.” I, Bosw., <emph>Life of
                            Johnson</emph>, 474, 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> 1791. <note>Boswell,
                                <emph>The Life of Johnson</emph>, 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> ed., I 474
                            (6/4/1775).</note></p>
                    <p>Adam Smith, speaking of the ancient Chaldeans and Egyptians, says, “Whether
                        there ever was in those nations any thing which deserved the name of
                        science, or whether that <hi rend="underline">despotism which is more
                            destructive of leisure and security than anarchy itself</hi>, and which
                        prevailed over all the East, prevented the growth of philosophy, is a
                        question which, for want of monuments, cannot be determined with any degree
                        of precision.” <emph>Essay on the Hist. of Astronomy</emph>, p. 27.
                            <note>“The History of Astronomy,” § 3, in Smith, <emph>Essays on
                                Philosophical Subjects</emph>, p. 27.</note></p>
                    <p>See Hume’s <emph>Essay</emph>, Politics a science, for the passage where he
                        says that Free Governments, more than despotic ones, are oppressive to their
                        dependencies. <note>“That politics may be reduced to a science,” in
                                <emph>Essays</emph>, P. I, n. 3: “Free governments … are … the most
                            ruinous and oppressive to their provinces. … {A} free state necessarily
                            makes a great distinction {between general laws and particular acts of
                            oppression,} and must always do so, till men learn to love their
                            neighbours as well as themselves.”</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Liberty</hi> is another name for restraint. Where there is no
                        restraint, there is no liberty. That I may have so much liberty, another man
                        must have only so much. <note>Between 166v and 167r two pages have been torn
                            out.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch23" n="23" type="chapter">
                <head>Miscellaneous</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch23scrap168r" n="168r" type="scrap">
                    <p>“Nothing is so fatal to a nation as an extreme of self partiality, and the
                        total want of consideration of what others will hope or fear.” Burke, v. 7,
                        p. 170. <note><emph>Remarks on the Policy of the Allies with Respect to
                                France</emph> (1793), in <emph>Works</emph>, VII 170.</note></p>
                    <p>“Among precautions against ambition, it may not be amiss to take one
                        precaution against our <emph>own.</emph> I must fairly say I dread our
                            <emph>own</emph> power and our <emph>own</emph> ambition; I dread our
                        being too much dreaded. … Can we say that at this hour we are not
                        invidiously aggrandized? We are already in possession of almost all the
                        commerce in the world. Our empire in India is an awful thing. If we should
                        come to be in a condition not only to have all this ascendent in commerce,
                        but to be absolutely able, without the least controul, to hold the commerce
                        of all other nations totally dependent upon our good pleasure, we may say
                        that we shall not abuse this astonishing and hitherto unheard of power. But
                        every other nation will think we shall abuse it. It is impossible but that
                        sooner or later, this state of things must produce a combination against us
                        which may end in our ruin.” Burke, <emph>Remarks on the Policy of the allies
                            in 1793</emph>—Burke, v. 7, p. 183, 184.</p>
                    <p>The following sketches seem intended by Burke, the first as a miniature of
                        the British spirit of government, the second as that of the Old French
                        government, and the third, as that of the government of the philosophic
                        republicans.—“For such a <emph>preparatory</emph> government” (viz., on the
                        re-establishment of the monarchy in France by the arms of the allies) “no
                        slow-paced, methodical, formal, lawyer like system, still less that of a
                        shewy, superficial, trifling, intriguing court, guided by cabals of ladies,
                        or of men like ladies, least of all, a philosophic, theoretic, disputatious
                        school of sophistry.” Burke’s <emph>Works</emph>, v. 7, p. 186.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch23scrap168v" n="168v" type="scrap">
                    <p>“The true state of every nation is the state of common life. The manners of a
                        people are not to be found in the schools of learning, or the palaces of
                        greatness, where the national character is obscured or obliterated by travel
                        or instruction, by philosophy or vanity; nor is public happiness to be
                        estimated by the assemblies of the gay, or the banquets of the rich. The
                        great mass of nations is neither rich nor gay: they whose aggregate
                        constitutes the people, are found in the streets and the villages, in the
                        shops and farms; and from them, collectively considered, must the measure of
                        general prosperity be taken. As they approach to delicacy, a nation is
                        refined, as their conveniencies are multiplied, a nation, at least a
                        commercial nation, must be denominated wealthy.” Johnson, <emph>Journey to
                            the Western Islands</emph>, Banff. <note>In <emph>Works</emph>, VIII
                            228.</note></p>
                    <p>Lord Eldon’s indecisiveness accompanied with great knowledge, we are told of
                        the law, and great ingenuity. Were lord Eldon called upon to decide whether
                        532 multiplied by 786, or 610 multiplied by 639 is the greatest, would he,
                        do you think, feel any difficulty in deciding? A man is only indecisive,
                        when he does not see clearly. Lord Eldon cannot decide because his mind is
                        in the dark. When you say he is ingenious without being able to decide, you
                        say he is ingenious at groping in the dark. Suppose <del>a set of</del> two
                        men to be enclosed in a dark labyrinth—the one by his sagacity really
                        devises the means of getting out—the other thinks of a vast number of
                        things, but not one of them having the least tendency to get him out. Which
                        of the two is the ingenious man? To apply the word ingenious to lord Eldon’s
                        doubts or to the reasons which he hatches for them, what is it but an abuse
                        of the term, and an abuse which tends to hide and cover from contempt, by a
                        word importing praise, the miserable imbecility of his mind. Were a man on
                        sitting down to such a dinner as this, to go to his work and call up all the
                        reasons which by possibility might exist to render it unwise to eat—as, who
                        knows as to the dirt or cleanliness of the cook—as to the wholesomeness of
                        the beast from which the meat was taken—who ever knows another thing, its
                        freedom from poison. Who knows exactly the state of his own</p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch23scrap169r" n="169r" type="scrap">
                    <p>body, whether the seeds of a fever may not be in it, etc., etc. If any man
                        were to go to hunt out all such things with great pains and minuteness, it
                        would be easy for any intellect, the dullest and stupidest in the world, to
                        find out a multitude of things, which never occur to any other body, and
                        which in like manner, might be dignified with the name of ingenious.
                            <note>John Scott, first Earl of Eldon, 1751-1838, was Lord Chief Justice
                            of the Common Pleas, 1799-1801, and Lord Chancellor, 1801-06, and
                            1807-27; a brilliant lawyer, but infamous for his delays of court cases,
                            and his political conservatism.</note></p>
                    <p>“There will always be a part, and always a very large part of every community
                        that have no care but for themselves, and whose care for themselves reaches
                        little farther than impatience of immediate pain, and eagerness for the
                        nearest good. The blind are said to feel with more peculiar nicety. They who
                        look but little into futurity have perhaps the greatest sensation of the
                        present. A merchant’s desire is not of glory, but of gain; not of public
                        wealth, but of private emolument; he is therefore rarely to be consulted
                        about war and peace, or any designs of wide extent and distant consequence.”
                        Johnson, <emph>Taxation no tyranny.</emph>
                        <note>In <emph>Works</emph>, VIII 159-60.</note></p>
                    <p><emph>Moral Sanction.</emph> “Manners are of more importance than laws. Upon
                        them, in a great measure the laws depend. The law touches us but here and
                        there, and now and then. Manners are what vex or soothe, corrupt or purify,
                        exalt or debase, barbarize or refine us, by a constant, steady, uniform,
                        insensible operation, like that of the air we breath in. They give their
                        whole colour and form to our lives. According to their quality, they aid
                        morals, they supply them, or they totally destroy them.” Burke, <emph>Regic.
                            Peace</emph>, v. I, p. 426, 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>. <note><emph>Letters
                                on a Regicide Peace</emph>, n. I, in <emph>Works</emph>, VIII 172.
                            The title was squeezed in later. Same item referred to as <emph>Popular
                                Sanction</emph> at <emph>CPB</emph> I <ref target="cpb1ch5scrap28v"
                                >28v</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>“So averse to taking pains are most men in the search for the truth, and so
                        prone are they to turn to what lies ready at hand.” [G] Thucyd.,
                            <emph>l.</emph> I, c. xI, p. 15. <note>Thucydides, <emph>The
                                Peloponnesian War</emph>, B. I, c. 20, § 3, Loeb 37.</note></p>
                    <p>Calling bad names in ambiguous language—insinuating evil in language which
                        will bear two interpretations—what is it but venting calumny, under the base
                        advantage of a power to deny that one is venting it?</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch23scrap169v" n="169v" type="scrap">
                    <p>Johnson remarked, that madmen were fond of being with those whom they feared.
                        He also said that madmen in the milder stages of the disorder, were prone to
                        sensual indulgences: “but when they grew very ill, that pleasure was too
                        weak for them, and they had recourse to pain.” Boswell’s <emph>Life of
                            Johnson</emph>, ii, 563, 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> ed.
                            <note>(20/9/1777).</note></p>
                    <p>Boswell maintaining the dignity of a player said, “We must consider, too,
                        that a great player does what very few are capable to do: his art is a very
                        rare faculty. Who can repeat Hamlet’s soliloquy, as Garrick does it?
                            <emph>Johnson.</emph> Any body may. Jimmy there (a boy about eight years
                        old who was in the room) will do it as well in a week.” <emph>Ib.</emph>,
                        572. <note>(21/9/1777).</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch24" n="24" type="chapter">
                <head>Literary Anecdotes</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch24scrap172r" n="172r" type="scrap">
                    <p>The last volumes of the <emph>Spectator</emph> were published after a
                        considerable interval from the suspension of the former ones; of these about
                        a fourth were furnished by Addison. Dr. Johnson thinks them superior to all
                        that went before—Addison’s papers are said to be No 556, 557, 558, 559, 561,
                        562, 565, 567, 568, 569, 571, 574, 575, 579, 580, 582, 583, 584, 585, 590,
                        592, 598, 600—in all twenty three. <note><emph>Life of Addison</emph>, in
                            Johnson, <emph>Works</emph>, X 100fn. This is in a very early smooth
                            hand, very large, like the large flowery copperplate hand in the deleted
                            material at <ref target="cpb4ch22scrap160r">160r</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>Of Pope’s <emph>Homer’s Odyssey</emph> only twelve books were written by
                        himself. Of the rest, four Viz., 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>, 4<hi rend="sup"
                            >th</hi>, 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>2<hi
                            rend="sup">th</hi> were written by Fenton. And Broome translated the
                            2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 8<hi rend="sup"
                        >th</hi>, 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 16<hi
                            rend="sup">th</hi>, 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, to
                        whom the charge of writing all the notes was consigned.— <note><emph>Life of
                                Broom, ibid.</emph>, XI 50-1. Between 172v and 173r three pages have
                            been torn out.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch25" n="25" type="chapter">
                <head>On Attention Edinburgh College 179?</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch25scrap173v" n="173v" type="scrap">
                    <p>Notes of Lectures on Moral Philosophy</p>
                    <p>These observations upon our natural and acquired perceptions naturally lead
                        us to consider a part [?] of our mind which has been but little attended to
                        even by philosophers themselves. <note>From Dugald Stewart. See his
                                <emph>Outlines of Moral Philosophy</emph>, 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>
                            ed., 1793, P. I, § 3, ss. 41. In a very smooth early hand, much like
                            that in the deleted material at <ref target="cpb4ch22scrap160r"
                                >160r</ref>. Ink badly faded. This item is upside down, which
                            suggests that it may have originally been the first in the volume. Mill
                            was a student at Edinburgh from 1790 to 1797, see Bain, pp. 13-21.
                            Stewart taught philosophy there from 1785 to 1809.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="cpb4ch26" n="26" type="chapter">
                <head>Addenda to Volume IV</head>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch26editorial-note" n="26" type="editorial-note">
                    <p>The following material is on the <emph>reverse</emph> side of the items
                        pasted in at <ref target="cpb4ch15scrap99r">99r</ref> and <ref
                            target="cpb4ch22scrap162r">162r</ref>. The item on <ref
                            target="cpb4ch15scrap99r">99r</ref> is joined to the first on <ref
                            target="cpb4ch22scrap162r">162r</ref>. Words obscured by being pasted
                        down or cut away have been restored by reference to the texts concerned. It
                        is quite similar to material at <emph>CPB</emph> II <ref
                            target="cpb2ch1scrap8r">8r1</ref>, in that the hand is early (pre-1808),
                        the ink is now brown, the paper has a horizontal laid pattern. In
                            <emph>CPB</emph> V <ref target="cpb5ch20scrap102r">102r</ref>, the paper
                        has an 1802 watermark. Were one able to reconstruct the scraps in II, IV and
                        V of a similar nature, many could probably be shown to join as the first
                        item below does. Note that both the Swift, and Lyttelton’s <emph>Persian
                            Letters</emph> are to be found at <ref target="cpb4ch22scrap162r"
                            >162r</ref> above and at <emph>CPB</emph> II <ref
                            target="cpb2ch1scrap8r">8r1</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch26scrap99rv" n="99rv" type="scrap">
                    <p><del>Gulliver tells us that “there was always one in every herd of Yahoos who
                            had the appearance of a leader,</del></p>
                    <pb/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="cpb4ch26scrap162rv" n="162rv" type="scrap">
                    <p><del>and was always more [deformed in] body and more mischievous in
                            disposition than any of [the rest.] That this leader had usually a
                            favourite as [like himself] in body and mind as he could get, whose
                            [employment] it was to lick his master’s posteriors, and drive the
                            [female yahoos] to his kennels</del>.” <note>Swift, <emph>Gulliver’s
                                Travels</emph>, P. IV, c. 7. in <emph>WorksN</emph>, IX 293-4,
                                <emph>WorksS</emph>, XII 337.</note></p>
                    <p>x. <del>There was a curious [punishment] among the Athenians with respect to
                            [suicide]. They cut off the hand which did the deed, and buried it apart
                            from the rest of the body. Æschines in [<emph>Ctesiphon</emph></del>].
                            <note>Æschines, <emph>Against Ctesiphon</emph>, 244, Loeb
                        501.</note></p>
                    <p>… <del>women, is that of loving a fool. Marmon</del>. <note>Reference
                            unverified.</note></p>
                    <p>“<del>But I cannot bear to be thought guilty of concealment of the truth [in
                            any portion of my views, more especially in a work designed for the
                            profit of young men of sound disposition</del>.”] [L] Quintil.
                            <note>Quintilian, <emph>Institutio oratoria</emph>, B. III, § 6, ss. 64,
                            Loeb 441.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
